faithfully.
And some might be thinking, you know, it's too much.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall
and he will be the right
the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will
fall down and worship Him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of
Spirits. 1st Inoc, chapter 48 verses 4 through 5. The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is
nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free
of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know
reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live college show
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, and exterminators of locusts.
You're listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen DeYoung is with me from the sweltering and highly humid Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm here in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, cool and clean, 80 degrees Fahrenheit.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
Tonight, we're not taking any calls because once again, this is a pre-recorded episode.
God willing, we will be live with you again.
For our next episode, Father Stephen and I are pre-recording because we are, when you
hear this when it premieres, both in an apocalyptic location, also known as Phoenix, Arizona.
Based on recent temperatures, it might well be a gateway to the underworld.
What do you think?
Write in, let us know.
That said, we're not going to the underworld tonight, at least I hope not.
Pray for our repentance.
Tonight we're continuing our series on eschatology talking about the four horsemen of the
apocalypse, Gug and
make, Ag. And the armies of locusts from the north. Yes, it's enemies of God night on the
Lord of Spirits podcast, so sit your GPS for Armageddon. So my first question is whether the
forehorsement were doing real wrestling or not. Yes. Is that different from wrestling? I guess
wrestling, wrestling pro wrestling. Like are these different things? Well, see, here's the thing. I
Greco Roman wrestling.
But even at his present age, I would not accuse Ric Flair of not being real.
Not just in terms of the wrestling, but in terms of like his insane lifestyle at the
behavior.
He's been getting real, he keeps it real.
Yes, yes.
Even when keeping it real goes wrong, Ric Flair keeps it real.
It doesn't seem like it's...
to his credit. Not necessarily, right? Exactly. But I think he successfully made it to such an
advanced stage, shockingly. That's given said lifestyle that he's kind of in that category now
of like really old person where they could say, do horrible things and you're just kind of like,
God. Yeah, you know, he's wrote
another time. Yeah, he's he's
74 now. 74.
The sky was born in 1949.
Yep.
That's amazing.
Yeah.
And he had a, he sort of had a wrestling match last year.
He's been married five times.
Sort of.
Wow.
He sort of did.
Five times.
So God love him.
But yeah, there's also a four horse women of MMA
and a four horse women of the WWE.
No, see, I didn't know anything about that.
Yes, so there's far more to this.
You opened Pandora's jar on this one.
And yes, she had a jar.
I mean, yeah.
Read a cardboard box, sir.
It's a jar.
That's not even like a Mandela effect.
That's just nobody reads the original.
But yeah, it's also probably good since you declared it to be enemies of God night on
Lord of Spirits that no one can call in.
I didn't think of it that way, but now that you've said that.
Yeah.
Well, we would have probably gotten some interesting calls.
Hopefully, no enemies of God was actually called like James Earl Jones or.
Oh.
Wow.
went straight for the team's old
Yes, yeah.
Or the guy who invented Bit O'Honey.
Wow.
I'm taking it, you're not a fan of Bit O'Honey.
No one is a fan of Bit O'Honey.
I'm not.
It's like circus peanuts.
I don't mind circus peanuts.
But to me, Bit O'Honey is like...
It's like candy corn and...
and Tutsi Rolls and...
I don't know, something peanut flavored, all failing together.
Yeah.
But even even you, the best endorsement you could give to circus peanuts was a combination
of not as bad as Biddo Honey and I could tolerate them.
Wow.
Like no one is enthusiastic about circus peanuts.
It's amazing.
I mean, we're five minutes into our recording and already we've gone through.
pro wrestling and now where it you know garbage you can't eat or what likes yeah that's right
so that being said uh yeah uh the the four horsemen of the apocalypse right this shows up in uh
in the book of Revelation um people have this idea you know that there's there's war there's famine
there's pestilence, there's death, right?
These, and you would think if you turned to...
the book of Revelation, you would see this list, and here's their names, right? But that's
not what really happens in there actually if you actually read it. So we're gonna read it.
But there's a little bit of, a little bit that comes before it, right? You have to, there's
some frame that comes before Revelation 6, which is where the Four Horsemen are mentioned.
Right, right. Wrestling aside, my vote for best modern rendition of the biblical Four Horsemen
of the apocalypse.
was good omens. I haven't seen that. Where they're there. Well, you could have read the book,
where they're motorcyclists. Oh, there was Marvel comics. I mean, Apocalypse,
you know, he had his four horsemen. He turned to angelic. Yeah, I know. And, you know,
Walt time, it's it's great, but Apocalypse is the most disappointing villain ever. Like
years of build up. The dude is named Apocalypse. Right. Right.
like ancient Egyptian mutant, right?
You think this guy's gonna be awesome.
And then they finally face off with him
and like he turns his fists into giant hammers
right to hammer them.
Yeah, which that was a sandman thing.
Yeah, seriously bro, like that's what you got.
But Angel the Archangel was a kind of a nice
little legacy from that.
Yeah, but half rate, like half rate juggernaut, like seriously.
It's true.
I hear you.
I hear you now.
Anyway, Bible itself.
All right, so the four horsemen are in Revelation chapter six.
And to kind of set up what's going on though, we have to dip a little bit back into chapter
five.
So the four horsemen show up, make their appearance in the context of the opening of the
the seven seals.
So there's this in Revelation 5, there's this scroll in heaven.
This scroll is sealed with seven wax seals that have to be broken in order to open the scroll.
And first, there's sort of a liturgical ritual thing that happens in chapter 5
to try to locate the one who is worthy to open the scroll, to break the seals and open the scroll.
That person is ultimately determined to be the lamb who was slain, who is going to then
break these seals and open the scroll.
The scroll is a representation of sort of the deed or the title, the ownership or the
authority over creation, over the world, over the cosmos.
And this is why a worthy person.
needs to be found to again take possession of the creation, the created order, and to put it back
in order to restore justice to it. Yeah, I mean, this feeds into, it's the same theme as when Jesus
is about to ascend and he says, all authority or all power and heaven and earth have been given to me.
You know, I've taken it back from the dark powers that you surped it at this is mine. So this
This is just another way of depicting that same kind of thing.
Right. And remember, as we've talked about now, several times on the show, to judge
is to put things back into the proper order that justice represents. Right. So this
taking of possession is also a judgment. Right. It's a putting things back the way they're
supposed to be after a situation of injustice has prevailed for some time. And things are
out of order and not the way.
that they should be. And so in chapter six, as the lamb opens the first four seals, breaks
those first four seals after each one, one of the four horsemen sort of appears. Yeah.
And you get behold a lot in English translations. Behold. Which in Greek is Yvul, right? Although
I like I love a good read low
low. Yeah, yeah. And what this is all covering for is actually a word in the Hebrew Bible,
Hine. And if you want to really irritate a Hebrew professor of any stripe, translate the word
and Hene as behold with a big exclamation point after it.
So it is related.
to one of the Hebrew verbs meaning to see, which is why it gets translated as Idu, right,
this idea of like look. But the idea behind the word is that it's only quasi-translatable.
It's supposed to give a sense of immediacy or suddenness or kind of a surprise twist,
That's right.
And it's not totally dissimilar from how we use the word look in the sense of if you and
I were talking and we were going back and forth and all of a sudden I said look, right?
I wouldn't be actually telling you to look at something.
I would just be it would be like to get your attention.
Attention.
Yeah.
Like hey, right?
Right.
Yeah, which I mean like in you know, in Old English, there's a word like this, which is
which is the first word of a number of different poems,
including bass.
Wolf. And I mean, it is the ancestor of our modern English word, what? But there's a lot
of debate about how to translate the word and it seems to be like, listen up, pay attention.
You know, hey, it's not just an interjection. It's definitely a call for attention. Right?
Right. Right. And yeah. So as each of the horsemen shows up, you get this behold.
right. But it's tried that you could almost translate like boom. Right. Right. He opens
the seal and boom. There's a right. There's a writer out of horse. Right. You could do
bottoming bottom boom. I guess. The good old Victorian hey presto. Yeah. Yada yada yada.
whatever it is.
Every want to do it, but that's the idea is this sense of immediate.
So it's not like you see somebody riding up in the distance like they're coming from
some place and then they show up. It's just bang there they are. Yeah, yeah, where do
they come out of? We don't know. Be old. There was a white horse. Right, right. So, then
the question is, so who are these guys who are popping up during these first four seals?
uh
because seals five, six and seven are different
and we're gonna mention a little later, seal five,
but there aren't seven horsemen of the apocalypse, right?
This is four out of the seven seals.
And as Father Andrew already mentioned,
you may have in your head based on old X-Factor comics
or Good Omen's or some other thing,
War, famine, pestilence.
and death, right, as the names of the four horsemen,
but actually in the text, in Revelation six,
only one of them is actually named.
Only one of them is said to have a name.
Yeah, and that's death.
Yeah.
The other three not only aren't named,
but aren't even said to have a name.
That's sick, right?
So.
So they're identified in the text based on the descriptions that St. John gives for each
of them, right, the details of their description.
And where I say the details of their description, it's not like he spends, you know, a long-ish
paragraph giving all these details.
No.
We're talking about a short, relatively short sentence, right, where he gives a few details,
that are sufficient for his office.
audience to understand who and what he's talking about.
Right? So we have received those names,
Pestilids, War, Famine and Death.
We received the other three other than death through the Christian tradition.
Right? But not from the text itself,
but there also those aren't sort of
those aren't, well, this church
father or that church father or
this group of church fathers or
even all the church fathers agree
that this is who they are and
that's why that's who they are.
As we mentioned, the imagery that
Saint John uses, that we're going
to go through here, the imagery he
uses is imagery that's found not
only in the culture surrounding the
all the new tests.
but also within the Old Testament tradition itself.
Right?
This is true in general of the Book of Revelation.
Well, so the biggest reason people probably
misunderstand the Book of Revelation
is that they're trying to interpret it
based on a recent newspaper or news broadcast,
I guess, or...
the internet. But the second biggest reason why people misinterpret the book of Revelation
is that by and large we are familiar enough with the Old Testament, especially with the Old
Testament prophetic books. Yeah, so we don't get the references. Right. So all of their relatively
Things that look like relatively brief passing things to us when we're reading Revelation.
that were all that the original
hearers needed to know exactly
what St. John was talking about.
Yeah, and I mean, like an example
from our own time and day might be, you know,
if you're watching a cartoon, right?
And suddenly, you know, Mickey Mouse
comes on the screen and walks off.
You know, you immediately recognize Mickey Mouse.
You have some idea of who his character is
where he kind of fits within the whole Disney thing
and all that kind of stuff.
when he walks on, you don't need to have it explained to you. This is a mouse, even though number one,
he, in a lot of ways he doesn't look like a mouse. He looks more human than a mouse.
You don't need to have that explained or even what his name is, right? Like you see him,
you just know who he is. So, I mean, this is part of what St. John is doing is he's putting up these
characterizations so that the people of his time would say, oh, I recognize this guy.
Right. Right. Right. Or if some character on a show.
So, rips their shirt open and they have another shirt on underneath that has their first
initial.
Yeah.
We all know it that really big on the chest.
Means.
We all know this is a reference to super rad.
Yeah.
Right.
Even if that initial is like a G or a B. Yeah.
That's on their chest.
Yeah.
And it invokes the whole Superman, not necessarily his story, although some cases, but
like the idea of him, you know, the hero that's that's disguised and all this kind of
stuff. You know.
Right, right. Whereas if you had no idea who Superman was you'd never heard of Superman and someone did that
You'd have no idea what it meant. Yeah, and you might come up with all kinds of weird potential interpretations, right?
Because you didn't have the background
Yes in terms of why they did that and what that represented, right?
So the context
for all of Revelation including the forehorsement is
first of all the rest of the scriptures.
And then second after that, the world in which the scriptures were written, right?
So that said, for a couple reasons, one of them being he is the guy who gets identified and named
in the text of Revelation itself. We're going to actually start with death.
Yeah, you know, he's the fourth one. Yeah. He's the fourth and last one to show up.
And so he shows
up in verses 7 and 8 of chapter 6.
All right. When he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature
say, Come, and I looked and behold a pale horse, and its rider's name was death, and Hades
followed him. And they were given authority over a fourth of the earth to kill with sword
and with famine and with pestilence, and by wild beasts of the earth.
You almost King James.
I know, I almost as followed after him, you know, followed
with him. You wanted to. No, it's just that King James is the Bible in my head. It's
what can I say? But is it the only Bible in your head? Well, it's true. It's gotten a little
muddled. So this one, right? Obviously, it's a writer's name was death. That's pretty
on the nose, right? We're told who this is.
Hades.
following him. And the imagery here is a Hades as a dog or a beast or something that's
following after the guy on the horse, right? As if it were in a hunting party or something,
right? And notice that they're given authority over a fourth of the earth to kill
with sword famine and pestilence.
That would be the other three, right?
That we're going to talk about.
So that would be the other reason why we're starting with the fourth one is that
death here kind of gives us some context for all four.
Yeah, there's this sense that the other ones are instrumentalized by this one.
Right. So in the Greek, right, the word for we have for death is thonatos.
And of course, we also have hideies, the Greek word for which is hideies.
these. Um, are these. Um, so, uh,
I hate these as kind of obvious, right?
But the sort of easy identification then to make would be,
well, if St. John is appealing to sort of elements and concepts in the broader culture,
surrounding the scriptures and surrounding his original hearers at the end of the first century,
Then this would be a reference to maybe the Greek God, Thanatos.
There's a Greek God named Thanatos and the Greek God, Hades.
Right? Like maybe that's just the, he's making just this direct connection.
The problem with that idea is that the way he hears describing Thanatos and Hades
doesn't really match the concepts of
Thautotocin Hades, the Greek gods.
Yes, such that it doesn't look like he's referring to those because those would give a very different
impression than the one he's clearly trying to give in context. So, Thonatos is
or was the brother of hypnos. hypnos is one of the gods of sleep. He's the god of like deep dreamless sleep,
Don't they got of dreams?
Don't they got of hypnosis?
No.
Not the God of hypnotism.
No, though that is where the word comes from.
Yeah.
So I just wanted to check if the etymology always tells us no.
Well, sort of.
Sort of.
Yeah.
It's related concept.
Well, you could definitely see how the concept of a deep dreamless sleep and death are related,
right?
Yeah.
Right.
that also the reason we bring up.
Hypnosis, the brother, that connection there is that this also has to do with the type of
death with which Thanatos is associated.
He's not just death in general.
Right.
So, you know, we have various depictions of death whether it be a gothie teenage girl
or the grim reaper, or these different depictions.
And Thanatos was specifically the God who was associated with death in old age.
Right? The idea of, you know, the death that comes to people like a deep dreamless sleep at the
end of their life, where they're old and tired and full of years and surrounded by their families.
And, right? That's the kind of death that he represented, right? He sort of like the grim
Reaper in the dog meme.
over the dog ass, some if he was a good boy. This is like the that kind of death, right?
And in fact, this, unlike most gods of death and most cultures,
Thanatos actually was worshiped. There were shrines and stuff to Thanatos in
Greek and Roman areas. And that was because people would go and make offerings to Thanatos because
That's the kind of death they want it. Yeah, usually you
wouldn't worship a death god because you kind of want to ward him off.
Right, right. But this was, this was the kind of death you wanted.
And everyone was kind of aware that they were mortal except maybe the emperor.
And so, you know, this is, this is the one you were looking for, right?
That definitely does not sound like the figure St. John is describing your revelation.
Yeah. Killing with the sword and famine and pestilence and wild beasts. Right. Kind
of the opposite. Right. That's my mind. And and Haiti's the same way. Right.
Hades is being depicted as sort of trailing after like this beast or something. And Hades
was one of the the big three gods. Oh yeah. In Greek religion. Along with Zeus and Poseidon.
right where they divided up the earth after they
took care of the Titans and their dad, Kronos and Zeus became the ruler of the sky and therefore
the surface of the earth that's under the sky. Hades got the underworld, Poseidon got the seas.
So in the Greek understanding, Hades was definitely not some servant of
of Thanatos, right?
If anything, the other way around, right?
Right, right.
So this doesn't really match up.
But if you go back to ancient,
Semitic religion, if you go back to
Canaanite religion, Phoenician religion,
and you go to their God of death,
whose name to death, Mote.
You find somebody who looks a lot more similar, right?
because moat was both the God of death who went around dealing death and he also ruled over the
underworld as a sort of tyrant. And so he was after capturing, killing, right, and slaving
Everybody, right? Remember he eats bail in the bail cycle.
And so this kind of idea that St. John is describing with death here is much closer to
moat and that kind of idea of God.
Moat is also often depicted as or with alongside of him some kind of beast or creature with a
big open gaping maw that represents shield the grave, the underworld, right?
the home house who sort of swallowing up his victim.
right, like he's chucking him in there. Or sometimes he's just the one swallowing
like with bail in the bail cycle. But also importantly, in terms of this
description by St. John, Mo also had a little retinue of gods, right? He had an
entourage who traveled around with him. And in the way that St. John
sort of depicts the sword and famine and pestilence going out in front of death and sort of killing,
right, repensals or whatever, however you want to imagine it, right? And then him sort of collecting
them up and feeding them to Hades, sort of how St. John is depicting this. That's very much
and keeping with moat who had these other gods of pestilence and of famine and of war.
within around him, right, who sort of fed him the living, right?
So it seems pretty clear that, and the way death is described helps us see this, that St. John
is drawing on this earlier sort of canonite structures. Yeah, but he's writing in Greek. So he's
is going to use the recwords to...
described right right. But as we're going to see in this section, this is true throughout
revelation, but in this section, there are a couple of plays where we'll especially see
he's basically writing in Hebrew in Greek.
Yeah, he's thinking in Hebrew and he's translating in his head and he's writing it in Greek words.
Right. And not just any Hebrew, but specifically the Hebrew of the Hebrew prophets. And we're
gonna see he's getting his dep-
even though spoilers were going to end up saying all four of the horsemen are moldy old canonite gods.
The way he is thinking about them and presenting them in Revelation is filtered through the way they're presented in the prophetic literature of the Hebrew Bible.
Yeah, so he's not just presenting.
God's, he's presenting the Bible's take on pagan gods.
Right.
Yeah.
Which, of course, as we've said before, is the correction, right, and the reinterpretation
of what the pagans believed.
So having now looked at death, sort of the last one, will roll back a little bit.
We'll go back to the...
first of the four horsemen who comes out. Okay. And how he's depicted and then how we understand
who he is based on that depiction. All right. So for those keeping scored home, death came on a
pale horse. And here we go, Revelation 6.2. And I looked and behold, boom, a white horse. And
and its writer had a bow, and a crown was given to him
and he came out conquering and to conquer.
So yeah, that last little bit there conquering into conquer is exhibit A of what I was just
talking about of writing in Hebrew in Greek.
So in Greek that just sounds kind of weird.
You're using the same verb twice.
and the infinitive, right?
Which is it?
really a thing you would normally do in Greek, like you wouldn't show up for a meal and
be like, I came here eating and to eat. At least people would look at you odd, if you
did.
I'd like to speak in King James, which some of us sometimes do. But even then it would
be weird.
and set onto him. Yeah, but I don't think eating into
eat. That level of English. I think it'll
be the good if you took the Tartus
back there. They look at you oddly, if
you said I came here eating and do
eat. Now I'm going to start
googling through Shakespeare to see
if they said stuff like see if
there are any phrases like that.
I'll be right back. Yeah, it has
to be the exact same verb twice.
But this is a normal...
grammatical construction in Hebrew. Yeah. Where you use a verb and then you put the same verb
in the infinitive. It's called an infinitive absolute construction. Probably the most famous one of
these in the Hebrew Bible are most well known, I don't know that it's famous, but the most well-known
one is when God gives the command not to eat.
from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. And he says, well, it's usually translated
in English as on the day on which you eat of it, on the day on which you eat of it, you will surely die.
Yeah, right. But what it literally says in the Hebrew is, on the day on which you eat of it,
dying you will die or dying to die, right? You'll die a death.
something like that. And that's this same kind of construction. And the idea surely is actually,
there was actually a really good translation in the sense that it's kind of
and emphatic. Yeah, you're really going to die. Yeah. Like not, you know,
So, OMG, I just died when I saw whatever, right?
We should replace all these constructions with literally,
is what we should do.
That would literally.
You will literally die.
I'll always see Rob Lowe in my head now,
having watched Parks and Recreation all the way through.
Literally, I think there's not a single moment in that show
when he uses literally that it's literally
what the word that he needs.
Yeah, and he came out literally to conquer.
Right.
So yeah, so that's the idea there is it's it's this emphasis right this emphatic
idea
with the idiom
so
from the way
this fellow is described
it's it's pretty well a lock to identify him with the figure of Reshif
And we've talked about it.
And we have talked...
about Reshif before. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I think a couple of times. I can't listen to myself.
So I couldn't go check and be sure. But um, living your best child.
My wife. He is a prominent figure. In ancient Eryster religion,
shows up repeatedly in the Hebrew Bible.
But we only get, as I mentioned, a couple of descriptors.
We get that the horse is white, but we get that the rider has a bow
and he conquers things.
Right.
Reshiff, one of his primary titles
that describe him in the ancient literature is.
described as the horse rider. So that's one thing. And the other thing is, you
notice the rider has a bow of all weapons, right? And Reshiv is always depicted as
an archer. The arrow's element is critically important, right, to his whole, the
whole concept.
And Reshef was the ancient world of God of plague or pestilence. His name literally means
one who burns. And that was connected with fevers, which of course was a symptom for the
onset of plagues and pestilences and contagious diseases. Fevers are one of the signs of contagion.
It makes people over and over and over and over.
But he was also a god of war.
And it's not always obvious to us,
but in the ancient world especially,
but probably still to this day,
at least in many places,
there's a very close connection between war and plague.
We now know from the perspective of science
that a lot of this has...
to do with issues of sanitation.
When you have an army camped out at war, that's a prime breeding ground for disease because
you've taken a whole bunch of people from one place and brought them to another place
and then put them in close quarters with not great sanitation in the nation, military
camp.
At the same time, a lot of ancient warfare was laying siege to cities.
So what you do.
when you laid siege to a city was you cut off supplies going in, you cut off
sanitation going out. And so the people inside both due to malnourishment
affecting their immune systems and the sanitation issues caused by being
under a siege would have outbreaks of blanket disease within the city and
that's part of what would help break a lot of Sieges, right? It's just people
would have to stay closed up in the walls and
all die or they would have to surrender. So there was this connection right between disease
and warfare that allowed him to also be a god of war, a god whose favor would be sought
out by those going to war or who would be who those going to war would want to target
against their enemies. It's a tent of them.
Russia was so popular that he gets assimilated beyond sort of his home base, where he originates
in the Levant.
So in Canaan, Phoenicia, Aramea, Syria, right, this is where Reffershoorjali comes from,
that he gets assimilated into Egyptian religion.
and maintains his name and maintains his general appearance from West Semitic religions,
which is kind of unusual for Egypt. They continue to depict him as an azeatic, which is what they
called foreigners from the rest of the ancient Near East. He gets assimilated at least at Cyprus
into a hollow. So you get these early depictions of a hollow in cypress.
where he has the arrows and the arrows are said to bring plague.
He's referred to or there's a reference in the Iliad and book one lines 42 through 55 to Phoenician Apollo,
which is apparently Homer's way of referring to Rechef, right?
as he sees him as a particular hypostasis,
a particular localization of Apollo.
He's...
know, being a Greek, save the correlation, the opposite way from what it seems to have
been historically.
It seems Apollo seems to have been Greek Rechef, more the other way around.
But in the treaty between Hannibal, the Carthaginian general of the Phoenicians and Philip of
the king of Macedon.
Apollo is one of-
the gods who is invoked as a witness to the treaty, this Venetian Apollo, because he's seen
to be a god who they both share. And so can both appeal to him in some way. So he is of
some major significance. And so the imagery of Rachev as pestilence and his
arrows then gets picked up in a bunch of places in the Old Testament to describe
pestilence and plague. So for example, Deuteronomy 32 verses 23 and 24, God says,
I will pile evils upon them. My arrows will exhaust on them. They'll be wasted
with hunger, they will be devoured by Reshef and Ketab the Poisonous.
So this is God talking about his judgment against the wicked.
And you can see here language, we're gonna be coming back
to this of him sort of letting Reshef and Ketab,
who's another sort of play God sort of loose on them, right?
Sort of sicking Reshef on them as part of that judgment.
In Psalm 78 in the Hebrew 77 in the Greek, verse 48,
48 that song.
goes through it sort of meditates on the plagues on Egypt. And so in that
Psalm, when it gets to describe the seventh plague in verse 48, it describes
that plague as having given up the cattle to hail and the herds to the
rheships to to plague or to disease, right? It's sometimes translated in English, but the
the word there is literally the name of this.
the spiritual being. Habakkuk 3 verse 5 describes Deber who's another similar
kind of God of famine and trouble going before Yahweh and Resha following
behind following after him.
What Habakkuk is doing there and Habakkuk 3 is...
is he's describing that kind of
entourage a retinue that's usually
attributed to moat, right, where moat
has sort of these minions who go and
do these things.
And in Habakkuk, it's actually Yahweh
who is in control of those minions.
And again, that's an idea we'll come back to
a little later.
In Psalm 76, in the Hebrew,
So
25 in the Greek verse four. It's talking, God is talking there about putting an end to
war and to battle. And he says that he shattered the ref chefs of the bow. And this is kind
of typical, I know we've mentioned man two before who's the, who was the Egyptian God of
War, who was said to be the right arm of Ray. And so when you read in the prophets, a lot
of the prophecies.
in the Hebrew Bible. Again, Steve Gip talk about God breaking the right arm of Egypt.
Right? That's the idea of him, you know, be able to wreck their war God. This is the same kind
of thing, right? Resha of being this war God with a bow, right? It's saying God can snap him
the way you know snap a bow over your knee or something. Oh, it's it's first three by the way
I'm just checking. It's not for three. Oh, three. 76 three. Yeah. Well, that may be different
in the Greek and
Yeah, maybe that's true.
The verse numbering in a lot of the Psalms is different.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's funny.
One of the earlier verses you mentioned, the one in about the plague, actually it says,
most translations give it as the thunderbolts to the flocks or something like that.
But if you, you know, pull out your strongs at Concordance or the Blue Letter Bible on the
Internet, you can see it says, Reshift.
Yeah.
Yep, so...
Job 5 or 7, one of the descriptions of Job's afflictions talks about the sons of
Rashif that fly through the air.
That's sort of the image of, right?
The sons of Rashif would be the arrows that he shoots that carry the pestilence and the disease.
And, of course, I know we've talked about, I'm pretty sure this is one of the places where we talked about Rashif before.
in terms of Psalm 91 in the Hebrew 90 in the Greek, which is in the Dead Sea Scrolls,
that's of the six exorcism Psalms that they held or written by David, Psalm 91 slash
90 is the one that's actually canonical Psalm.
The other five we only know from Kumron.
So that exorcism Salmon verse 5 talks about the arrow
that fly by day. All of those, if you read the original Hebrew, are references. And this is, again,
I believe we've gone through this on the show and that's one of the places we talked about
Reshif. But, you know, the demon of Noon Day, all of those things, are references to particular
sort of demonic entities and the spirits of calamity in the ancient world.
Yeah. Although that one in particular doesn't mention, doesn't use the word Reshif,
but there is this idea.
the arrows that fly by day and, you know, it's their references to without actually naming
in that particular case.
Right.
And since it's in a list of very clear references, sometimes using the names of other,
right, demonic entities, it's a pretty clear link.
So some of you may have gone back and looked at that verse.
and been like in Revelation and said, you know, there's nothing actually in that verse in Revelation 6 about disease at all.
Right. Even though we all kind of call this one pestilence.
Right. Nonetheless, everywhere you look, that's what this horsewood is called.
And that
because even though I imagine most folks, not everybody,
but imagine most folks hadn't really heard of Reshef
before this show or some other similar show
or they read DDD or something, that identification
that we just sort of walked through has been held onto
in within the Christian tradition, even if it hasn't been made
explicit, right?
even if there isn't some place where
somebody sat down and said, yes, this is Reshift.
Da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da.
That's why we say that this horse made his pestilence, right?
The horse was just identified as pestilence.
That interpretation is continued and contained in the tradition.
And so this is, I think,
illustrative of how we work with
our only Orthodox tradition on this show a lot of the time.
We will sometimes, I don't know, we will sometimes.
Sometimes there are folks out there who assume that if they
listen to this show, for example, and hear something they've
never heard before, that either we're making it up or
that either we're making it up.
or this is some newfangled academic thing,
or something, and therefore can't be part
of Orthodox tradition somehow
because they haven't heard it before.
There's a bunch of problems with that.
One being, if you assume that anything you haven't heard
before is new, you're assuming you know everything.
But some people do, right?
Like that's the missing plank in your syllogism, right?
Right, I've...
heard this before, I know everything. Therefore, this is new, right? Like that's the only way to make
that syllogism work. It sounds like a boring life. Yeah. That's... As the person who actually knows
everything. Actually, there's that problem, right? But also the fact that our
holy tradition has maintained everything you need to understand the holy scriptures,
right? And every other part of our tradition, the fact that it's all contained there
doesn't mean it has all been made explicit to, for, and in every generation.
Yeah, or that there's some kind of manual somewhere where you can look at all up.
Right. Right. And so just like we as Orthodox Christians don't say,
Hey, just read the Bible, no interpretation needed, no teaching needed, no preaching needed.
Right?
I, at least, as a priest, read the gospel on Sundays at liturgy, and then I preach.
And hopefully, if I'm doing a half decent job, then whatever I'm preaching, I'm saying
the same thing that the gospel said.
Yeah, which is what the word...
humbly, omilia means the same. But what I'm trying to do is take what the gospel says and sort of
draw it out and explain it and lay it out to people and show how it applies to their life
and what's going on in their life and what they need to do based on it, right? And so the fact that
maybe no one, maybe no one has.
Let's just say no one has.
Let's leave out the you haven't heard, right?
Let's say no one has ever laid out the point
of a particular parable of Jesus,
exactly the way I did on a particular Sunday, right?
In Southern Louisiana, in the 21st century, right?
To a particular group of people.
That doesn't mean I'm actually doing anything different
or doing anything wrong.
Because I'm talking to a different group of people at a different time in a different place in a different setting.
Yeah, and then so the way, and say, and even though we wouldn't compare ourselves to the Holy Fathers of the Church,
we're at least trying to adopt their method, which I mean, this is what they
largely are doing is trying to explain the scriptures and explain the tradition to people and
sometimes they will do it in a way that's new but seeing the same thing as has always been said.
Right. Right. So yeah, it's not that we and the church fathers are not called to do different things. The church fathers are just really, really good at it. And I'm not. Right. That's the difference.
Right. Like they're really good at it. But they're doing the same thing. Right.
But yes, you can even compare, and this is the problem, this is why people have heard
me say, if understood correctly, the fathers never actually dis...
agree, right? Because the way that a particular passage of scripture needs to be drawn out and laid out and explained to a congregation in a certain economic and social group in 19th century Russia.
And the way it needed to be drawn out and laid out and explained to another congregation in Constantinople near the end of the 4th century is not identical.
It's the same scripture, it's the same teaching, but to make it plain, to make it understandable,
to apply it to what's going on, is going to look very different in those two different
historical and cultural contexts.
Yeah, I mean, I can give a really quick example, which is, like if you read St. Thea
von the Reklus, is a 19th century Russian saint, he writes a lot of letters to people.
He often talks about feelings, like having certain kinds of spiritual feelings.
in the fifth century didn't talk though.
at all. They weren't talking about it. They have a feeling. Go for this feeling, follow this feeling.
Now what St. Theophan means by feeling is not what late 20th 20th and early 21st century,
you know, post-Froidian ideas about feelings mean by feelings. But still like, it's a very
different kind of way of talking than that early stuff. Right. Right. Yep. And so here, even though yes,
you're not going to find a lot of church fathers.
talking about the ancient Canaanite God Reshif, directly in terms of revelation six. But as I
think we've shown, the fact that they identify this horseman with pestilence means they've maintained
that identification. Even if they're not making it explicit because making that explicit doesn't
that serve their purposes, or maybe they didn't even know that.
Yeah, they knew that this is pestilence, right?
They knew how to interpret and apply revelation,
but they didn't know anything about ancient Canaanite gods.
Yeah, it may just not be the thing they had read about
or heard about.
Yeah, that's one of the beautiful things
about our holy tradition is that one can just accept it,
right?
And know that you are in good stead, right?
And then having accepted it,
be-
coming apart of it, living within it, you can then start to explore it and go into the depths of it and the nooks and the crannies, right?
But the fact that you have an explored every depth and nook of crannie, because you never will in this life, right?
The fact that you have a done all that doesn't mean that you're like an ignorant Christian or something, right?
because if you have accepted it and you're living within it, you have the whole thing.
Yeah, exactly.
I don't need to know how my car works in order to drive it well.
I know some things.
Well, I mean, you know, there's certain things if you don't know,
you could really mess up your car.
Yeah, of course, but like I don't know how it just talks to my
fun out of gas on the side of the road.
I've heard that that could be an issue.
Yeah.
So all right.
Well, we've done, we've done death.
We've done pestilence two more horsemen to go and we've got some
other bad guys.
We're declaring our name.
I'll wait.
All right.
We'll be right back after this.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-A-F Radio.
Hi, do you know me?
I'm Father Stephen DeYoung.
new book, Kapakrify and Introduction.
extrabiblical literature is now available. A lot of Christians today divide ancient Jewish
and Christian literature into two categories. What's in the Bible? What's not in the Bible?
Christian East, however, has traditionally had a third category, a middle category. Books
that are read privately in the home. The Greek word for that is apocryphal. These texts
from the centuries before and the centuries after the incarnation of Christ that go beyond
even the larger cannons of Orthodox and Roman Cal.
Churches.
Reveal to us the religious world and theological framework of the apostles and early church fathers.
In this book, Apocrypha, I survey these works, which connect elements of liturgy, scripture,
iconography, patristic writings.
Familiarity with these works will enhance readers' understanding of the breadth and depth
of the Orthodox Christian faith.
Buy or copy of Apocrypha an introduction to extrabiblical literature at store.anxianfaith.com.
at store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
[♪ Music playing in background, music playing in background,
we're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung.
podcast.
we're talking in this case about the four horse from the apocalypse,
Gog and Megog, and of course, about locusts. So we've talked about two of the horsemen so far. We
talked about death and pestilence. So who's up next for our next boom slash behold slash
What? Slash low, you do, etc.
Or boom, shotgun lock?
No, that's what we're doing too far.
That's...
NBA Jam. I remember that game. I loved that game. That was a great game, actually. So,
you heard it here first, Father Andrew used to love sports ball game. That's true. We actually have
not too far from where I live. There is an arcade called Back to the Arcade with the requisite
back to the future looking logo and they have they have NBA
jam there. And, or is it jams? See, I can't remember now. And I showed it to one of my
sons when I was there. He didn't know what to make of it. But I was having all kinds of
nostalgia. And I was indeed saying, boom, shakalaka, which you get when you do like a big
high jumping dunk, you know?
Yes. Full rotation. Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah, I may or may not have all the arcade games in my living room.
I'm not sure if you can
either confirm nor deny.
Though there are people out there who can't confirm.
Amen.
So, yeah, so the third horseman who we're going to talk about,
the second one, to ride out.
And no, they are not plying at the streets of gold
and sending gold ships down into the...
checkbooks of TBN donors.
Sorry, late Paul Crouch.
I've heard that's a thing though.
He claimed so.
So, you know.
That's so good.
I mean, that is creativity right there.
Yeah, and maybe his wife's hair was to protect her
from the flying gold charts.
Who knows?
So, TBN shade on this episode of Lord's.
experience. So they don't mind. You know, I okay, now now you did it. I know someone who owns a copy
of the Heidelberg Catechism. Okay. One of the Dutch reform three forms of unity. Right. Okay,
Dutch reform Catechism. With a sticker in the front saying it's a free gift from Paul Crappchen.
Nice.
Actual artifact.
That's beautiful.
That should be in a museum.
Yeah, don't know how to happen.
For sure.
But there it is.
So war.
What is it for?
Absolutely nothing.
Original title for war and peace, by the way.
Just war.
four. What is the good for? Oh,
okay. Um, yeah, I don't know if,
if the horseman war is a low rider,
but the, uh, we hear about him in
versus three and four of chapter six,
as we mentioned, he's the third one.
We're going to talk about he's the second one
who appears. All right. Yes.
So, peel.
for death, white horse for pestilence, and now starting with verse three. When he opened the
second seal, I heard the second living creature say, come, and out came another horse, bright red.
Its rider was permitted to take peace from the earth so that people should slay one another,
and he was given a great sword. So the red horse of war.
And that's a great sword isn't big.
It's not like that sword's really great.
That sword's awesome.
Yeah, it's huge.
Huge source.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know if, you know, I mean, I know what everyone's
thinking, right, they're thinking dark riders.
They're thinking this must be one of those completely
disproportionate anime swords that's so giant the person
wielding it could not possibly lift it.
You're probably going too far with it.
So this rider, I didn't like this rider is...
war is not much of a stretch, right? So he takes peace from the earth, and if you take peace
away, what do you have? You have war. So the people should slay one another. That's war, right?
But the important element here in terms of identifying this rider with a kind of demonic
entity or entity in general from the Old Testament.
this sword. And specifically the way in which the sword is referred to in the Hebrew Bible.
There are a lot of places where the sword is used, where it's clearly not referring to
a sword, right, just a sword as an object.
And...
where the sword is talked about as being an entity,
as being something with agency that does things,
something that is sent, something which remains in a place
or in a family or among a people.
And so it takes a certain kind of special pleading
that modern people are very capable of,
but it takes a kind of special pleading to read it
as just being a metaphor.
Right.
Oh, there's there's just going to be like strife and violence.
Right. Um, and the problem with, I mean, let's get right to out to it. The problem with
thinking it is a metaphor is that strife or violence has to have an agent. Yeah, it doesn't just
happen. Right. Like someone's just standing their body, their own business and all of a sudden,
you know they
are physically injured by nothing in particular.
Right, like violence has to have an agent.
Right, and so if violence or strife or conflict is going to come into a family, a tribe,
a nation, right, between one of those and another of those, right, it has to have an agent.
There has to be some...
one who's actually doing it, right? And so there are places in Scripture, very clearly,
where God sends an agent to do something, sometimes something violent, right, like sending
in the descendants of Abraham to root out the giant clans, right? There's the agent, right?
when God sends.
Nebuchadnezzar to take Judah into exile for their sinfulness, right?
Or he sends the Assyrians to wipe out the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
There you've got your agent, right?
But there are other places where God just says he's going to send the sword.
Yeah.
Where the sword is the agent.
So that's not speaking as an analogy for violence in general, or bloodshed in general.
that speaking of a kind of entity, a spiritual entity, meaning it's a spirit because it has agency, an entity with agency that's going to inspire and cause this violence and bloodshed and strive to happen.
Relatedly, another term that's used beside the sword in a similar kind of way is the way
the Hebrew word for blood is used when it's used.
in the plural. So not dumb but domine which literally means bloods. Right. But which, when used in
the plural represents not just again metaphorically, well, bloods plural, lots of blood, bloodshed,
right. But referring to a kind of agent connected to to bloodshed. So to give you an idea,
We're not going to read all the...
We're not going to go through all these, but to give you an idea of how common these references to the sword as an agent are in the Hebrew Bible.
Here is a partial list. This is a partial list.
Okay, and I'm just going to check the an impiate. I'm going to go through it.
I'll speak.
You're going to look it up later.
You pause this.
If you really want to look at everything, single one up.
Exodus 5 verse 8, 22 verse 24. Leviticus 26 verses 7 and 8 and 25.
8 and 25.
Number 14, verse 43.
Number 20.
18, Deuteronomy 28, 22, and 32, 25. Second Sebbial, 2, 26, 11, 25, 12, 10, 18,
verse 8, Ezra 9, 57, Job 5, 15, 20, 22, 29, 27, verse 14, 39,
verse 22, Psalm 22, 20, Psalm 37, verse 15, Psalm 63, verse 10, Psalm 76, verse 3,
78, 62, and 64. Some 144, verse 10, Isaiah 1, verse 20, 31, verse 8, and 37, verse 7.
Bingo. Yeah. And there are others, right? But that should give you an idea of how common this is,
to say, talk about the sword as this agent, the spiritual agent, right? And often it is,
the thusword is associated with verbs like devour, consume, right? This idea of devouring,
and consuming lives.
Right, a la moat in the hell mouth, right?
And
So here we can kind of see the pattern emerging
Right, this is gonna hold true what we get to fam and also
that
These other three
These are sort of the three ways you don't want to die
Right
So the the blessed way to die
the Hebrew Bible is old, full of years, surrounded by your grandchildren and great-grandchildren,
right, around your table.
That's the blessed way to die, right?
That's the way the patriarchs die in Jesus.
Gathered unto his fathers.
Right.
That's how you want to die.
Well, the ways you die other than that, the ways you die short of that, the way you miss
that blessing are what? Violence
disease, starvation, right, in the ancient world. And in a
graarian context, we may not think about it starvation as much as
we used to. We're also not living in an agrarian context, right?
There are parts of the world that still famine and starvation are
very real concerns. Even if they art for us in a lot of the
countries that will be listening to this in English. But in the
the ancient world they were for everybody.
Right. So these three kinds of death, particularly, these are like the bad deaths.
These are the deaths you don't want. Violence certainly being one of the chief among them.
Now, bloods, when bloods is used in the plural, it's a little more nuanced because the bloodshed here isn't just violence,
ones. But
It's a kind of, or first to a kind of debt related to vengeance for spilled blood.
The idea being if a person is spilled innocent blood, they've committed a kind of a paradigmatic
injustice.
a person who should be alive, right?
It should be part of the world.
the social order, but because of you is dead. Right. And so this is a paradigmatic injustice.
And one of the problems with it is a paradigmatic injustice is, right, if I steal money from you,
there's a relatively easy way to put that back to justice. Right. Give them money back.
I give the money back. Right. I can't give life back to someone if I've murdered them.
Yeah.
So what's the only way to kind of rectify that?
Blood for blood.
Right, for me to die too, right?
And so this isn't just a concept in the Hebrew Bible.
This is a concept everywhere in the ancient world.
Yeah, and even everywhere in the world, even as you go on and on and on, like even the ancient
Germanic people have the idea of the where go
weird guild, which means the human price, you kill somebody, you can pay their family
basically is what it comes down to. And the idea of it was to try to prevent feuds.
You know, like, we'll look at blood feud.
Pay us off and we don't have to have a blood feud.
Yeah.
So, but this was an ancient Near East. This in particular had this, uh, care, that there
were seen to be sort of demonic.
spiritual beings who are going to enforce this kind of justice.
So it wasn't just a question of law, right?
And being caught by some kind of authority and being executed, or being murdered by a
family member of the victim even.
But some of these, because we're seeing this so heinous, that you get.
So what probably the most example of which people would be most aware, most of our listeners
This would be in the context of...
Greek tragedy the way the theories function.
Someone commits a patricide or a matricide or a
fratricide.
And this is sort of not just because it's related to the
family, it's not only murder, it's murder, that's a form of
high sacral age.
And so even if you don't get caught, the
and use well.
sort of come up out of Hades and drag you down with them, right?
And tear you apart.
There is this kind of vengeance, right?
It's like cosmic, these demonic entities of cosmic vengeance,
which is not unrelated to how, for example,
most 1980s horror movies function.
They're very similar to Greek tragedy, that respect.
Um.
all the non-virtuous kids are the ones who end up dead.
Right?
All the ones who sleep around and use drugs and that kind of thing,
they all end up getting toward the pieces by the,
the sort of cosmic entities, right?
Whereas the ones who are virtuous are, are, end up safe.
There's even a reference.
in the Greek of Psalm 87 to the Furies.
Yeah, which, I mean, this is one of the six Psalms
that has read at Mattins and in the translation used
in at least in the Etiocanarctisus of North America,
there's the line, thy furies have passed upon me
and thy tears have sorely troubled me.
So the idea that the furies belong to God
and are connected to him.
You know, yeah. And and that this always is facing this torment, right?
It's sort of because of what he's done.
Um, is also what David is referring to in Psalm 51 and the Hebrew 50 in the Greek verse 14.
It's usually translated as something like delivery me from blood guiltiness in the English.
But literally in the Hebrew it's delivery me from bloods.
And this is that Hebrew idiom.
The idea is that it's not just that David feels guilty.
Right? It's that having killed Eureia
and taken Bathsheba as his wife,
he is liable to that blood.
Right? There is this sort of metaphysical debt.
Right? That he has.
He has on his soul, right, that he needs to be, and he needs to be delivered from the consequence
of that by God.
And of course, it goes, the first example to it, the Bible goes all the way back to Genesis
4 and Abel's blood crying up out of the ground.
Yeah.
Against his brother, K for justice.
And this kind of factors in in Genesis 37, verses 22 through 26.
Joseph's brothers are kind of trying to decide what to do with him.
Remember, some of them want to just kill him, right?
And go double to the desert somewhere.
But a couple of his older brothers have some concerns about that.
Yes, okay.
So this is starting with the verse 22.
And Rubin said to them,
"'Shed no blood, throw him into this pit here in the wilderness,
but do not lay a hand on him,
that he might rescue him out of their hand to restore him to his father."
So when Joseph came to his brothers, they stripped him of his robe, the robe of many colors
that he wore, and they took him and threw him into a pit.
The pit was empty, there was no water in it.
Then they sat down to eat, and looking up, they saw a caravan of Ishmaelites coming from
Gilead with their camels bearing gum, balm, and mure on their way to carry it down to Egypt.
Then Judah said to his brothers, what profit is it if we kill our brother and conceal his
blood?
See, that's this idea that, like, look, we can't kill
them because bad things will
happen to us if that, you know,
because the blood. Yeah, and so
we can't do this. They know what
will happen like with Able. And so,
you know, they're willing to go
sell them a display for any
shift, but they won't. They don't
want to spill any blood. Yeah.
And of course, in the context of
Revelation 6 itself, the fifth seal,
the seal after.
the four horsemen is when that is open, the souls of the martyrs cry out from beneath the
altar in heaven asking how long, O Lord, right, they cry out for justice, specifically over their
shed blood. And Revelation 6 uses the same verb for slay when it talks about war, the horsemen,
slaying right people out of the earth and the
have been slain. So war and the other
horsemen are part of the balancing of the
scales of justice there for those who have been
slain unjustly. Now there's going to be this
slayer who is sort of unleashed on the
earth to avenge those who have been slain.
track come up with a metal band.
for that but it just wasn't coming to me but...
What, I mean the slayer, come on.
I know, I'm not a...
I'm a heaven.
Actually a big slayer.
Rainier blood?
Fan, so...
I know, I'm so disappointing.
It's okay.
Are you sure at least go listen to Torey Amos's cover
of Rainier blood?
Wow.
Which is a thing, which is real.
So
This is also this idea of
shavings shed blood that
that blood
contracting this kind of debt
right of violence.
The pursuit lives by the sword, dies by the sword, right?
The sword.
The is also where we get some of the language, for example,
in Matthew 20, verse 28, or in verse 22, verse 28,
in first Timothy 2.
of the blood of a sacrifice as a kind of ransom, right?
The idea of it cleansing or purifying from that sort of debt
incurred by having shed blood.
So then the fourth horsemen we're going to talk about,
the third one who comes writing out is famine.
famine. All right. Again, Revelation 6 verses 5 and 6. When he opened the third seal, I heard
the third living creature say, Come, and I looked and behold a black horse, and its rider
had a pair of scales in his hand. And I heard what seemed to be a voice in the midst
of the four living creatures saying, A court of wheat for a denarius and three quarts of
barley for a denarius and do not harm the oil and wine.
I mean, there's another one, another one of those where like we identify this as famine,
but it's not super obvious just from this text.
This is about famine.
Like, okay, he's got, he's got scales in his hands, and he's talking about buying food,
but you know.
Yeah.
Right.
So, this is the Hebrew word for famine is Rob.
And Raav was not coincidentally the third figure in Moats, Retinue, in the ancient
Phoenician and Canaanite stories, and named literally Famin.
The idea here going on with the scales, these are market play scales.
So scales come up a lot when you read...
the profits. Yeah. In this
context, scales in the marketplace,
using just balances, just scales,
just weights, right?
Because it's not like
you walk into a village,
there's not some massive authority
you could come and say,
okay, this is how much exactly
how much a shackle weighs.
And this guy's shackle,
it is ballot scale is heavier
it should be or this was.
is lighter than it should be. Right? Like there's no one to go around enforcing that. Right.
Right. Um, hypothetically we have that now. I'm somewhat suspicious that at no time recently
has anyone been to any of our local gas stations and actually measured a gallon of gas to make
sure it's really a gallon. Hypothetically they do that. But they definitely did not do anything
like that in the ancient world. Right. And so the way someone, the primary way someone
was dishonest in business when you're trading because you're primarily trading in the
ancient world by close to pure bartering, right, is by fudging weights, right, by, you know,
Yeah, yeah, I'm giving you this much of that and you're actually giving them less right right
So there's this notion of cheating.
Yeah.
Going along with it.
Right.
And so that, of course, for obvious reasons, right,
the people who most got taken advantage
over the actual world were the poor and the powerless, right?
So people who were in poverty in general, especially orphans
at widows, because orphans at widows
couldn't even take you to court over it, right?
There were people who could be exploited.
And so again and again, you see these things about people being exploited.
The particular examples we get here are meant to give us the idea that food is so expensive
that people can't afford it.
So a denarius was one day's wages for workers.
worked for something like a wage.
Right?
A lot of people didn't work for a wage.
They're huge swath of people, subsistence farming.
But for people who work for a wage
and who then use that wage to go and get food
and the other things they needed in the marketplace,
a denarius was one day's wage.
So if you think about, you could get a court of wheat
for one day's wage, you have to work all day
just to get a court of wheat.
You have no money for anything else now.
Right. So this is the idea behind the scales and this being shouted vis-a-vis the marketplace
is that this isn't just to represent like, oh yeah, you're going to have bad crops for
a couple years, but that that's going to produce a chain reaction that's going to destroy
the markets, the economy, right, that existed at the time.
and everyone suffers then.
Yeah, so this is...
describing like the Great Depression, it's a should equivalent, right?
Where it's going to reach and touch everybody, right?
And famine could be a force for a kind of justice in the same way
that we were just talking about violence being, right?
In the sense that, well, this innocent person was murdered.
and so now the murder is dead too.
which is a kind of justice, not the ideal form, but a kind of it.
In the same way, the people who have oppressed the poor deprive them of their wages,
profited off of their hunger, oppressed the orphan in the widow. When this happens,
right, everyone is affected. They don't have any food either.
Right, those who have become rich and wealthy. And so they're sort of an equalizer.
of outright famine like this describes that it's everyone. Right. And so there's a sort of justice
to those who have oppressed and starved the poor now starving themselves, not the ideal kind of
justice but a kind nonetheless. And not only is Raab or famine seen as being part of
motes retinue but especially in the prophet Jeremiah you see him pair
together famine in the sword sometimes famine and the sword and plague the
fright all three together often just famine in the sword some examples I
will then impede them again and these are all Hebrew references I'm not going to
with both references.
I love that ven and be is now a verb.
Yes.
Jeremiah 2 verse 34 verse 10, 5 verse 12, 9 verse 16, 14,
verses 12 through 16, 15, verses 2 and 3, 16, verse 4.
21 verses 7 through 9, 24, verse 10, 25, verse 16,
and 27 through 29, 32 verses 24 through 26, 42,
verses 16 through 22, and 44 verses 12 through 18.
Are some examples?
Right.
And what these examples have in common is that they present famine in the sword and where it's also added pestilence or disease or plague as being these kind of spiritual forces that are unleashed by Yahweh the God of Israel as a form of judgment.
And that's unleashed in a very literal sense.
They're often portrayed as sort of these beasts
that accompany him who he has on a leash.
Right? Think of the Satan...
in Job. Right. He wants to do stuff to Job. He has to get a
permission and then he's given limits. Right. Yeah. Um, and the
idea is that God is sort of restraining these things from us
and protecting us from these things. But that eventually there
comes a time where without repentance, where he will stop
restraining them, at least he'll restrain them less. He'll let
them come into our lives, our families.
our tribe nation, whatever, in order to bring about that repentance, that so far we have not,
we have not shown. And a good example of that dynamic of God, sort of unleashing these forces
out of the world to go bring about justice, and one that sort of clearly prefigures what St. John
is doing with the Four Horsemen is actually in Zechariah 6 versus 1 through 8.
Yeah. So this...
is kind of the first appearance, the forehorsement,
although a little different.
So starting with verse one, again, I lifted my eyes
and saw and behold, four chariots came out
from between two mountains.
And the mountains were mountains of bronze.
The first chariot had red horses, the second black horses,
the third white horses, and the fourth chariot
dappled horses, all of them strong.
And I answered and said to the angel who talked with me.
What are these, my Lord?" And the angel answered and said to me,
These are going out to the four winds of heaven after presenting themselves before the Lord of all the earth.
The chariot where the black horses goes toward the North Country, the white ones go after them,
and the dappled ones go toward the South Country.
When strong horses came out, they were impatient to go and patrol the earth,
and he said, Go, patrol the earth. So they patrol the earth. Then he cried to me,
behold, those who go toward the north country have set my spirit at rest.
in the North country. So it's chariots in this case that seem to have multiple horses each.
But the colors are there again. Yeah. Dappled instead of pale, you know, colors are always
kind of a, an iffy question in the Eastern world, but an iffy text, you know, but, but,
but, yeah. So, but you see the issue here, right, is that there's something going on in
the north, go figure.
the North. It's always those guys. Right. That is disrupted justice. Right. And so these
horsemen are let loose. They're sent into the North. And then once they're done, God
spirit is at rest in the North. They've taken care of the issue. Right. The judgment has
taken place. So these powers, right, and his and his pals, right.
himself was
not sort of worshiped or invoked in the ancient world because you just wanted to keep death
away from you mostly.
Right.
And this is nasty, violent, untimely death.
Yes.
This is not like Thanatos with the Greeks.
The other, like, Reshev Raov, right, the sword, this kind of thing, these were the subject
of worship and invocation.
And that...
in sort of two ways, right?
So you get sacrificial worship with these gods,
either sort of defenses, defensive,
like, hey, be happy with us.
Leave us alone, right?
Here, have some meat instead of us.
And or, hey, our enemies over there,
why don't you go after them?
Yeah, right.
Right.
And that is.
that element and then of course we're using what we would call magic right so amulets,
bowling, cantations, curses and that kind of thing the same thing right ward them off from you
send them after the guy you don't like right yep um that kind of thing so the way they're
discussed in the Hebrew Bible though of course as we've seen now is different right all of these
These forces are controlled by Yahweh, the God of Israel.
in the Old Testament. It's not that they're not forces, it's not that they're not demonic, it's not that they're
some kind of materialist function of something or other, right? But they're controlled by Yahweh,
the God of Israel. And when they're released into the world, they're released at his timing for
his purposes, right? And there are always limits put on it. Yeah. We'll go joke again, right? And so
So regardless of what may be happening,
you, to your nation, to your tribe, to your clan, to your people, right? The only thing
you need to do from the perspective of the Hebrew Bible is repent and worship. You all
way they got to Israel. Yeah. You don't offer worship to those other gods to
placate them. Don't use magical incantations and stuff to control them or, you know,
be faithful to God.
And so, this is really the old testament
or the Hebrew Bible version of the Odyssey.
Yeah, the Odyssey being the explanation
for why bad stuff happens.
Yeah, God is good, God is all powerful,
bad stuff happens, right?
Right.
And so the understanding is that God
is not the
direct agent of any of these evils. Right. But that these demonic powers who have power in the
world because of human wickedness and evil, God unleashes at times into varying degrees to bring
about repentance, right, to bring about transformation, to bring good, to use them sort of against their
will to bring good out of human evil.
So the ultimate agent of all wickedness in the world in the Hebrew Bible is humans.
And even the demons who are in this middle space are being used by God for our good if we
we allow it to bring us to to repentance.
And so what
St. John is doing here with the Four Horsemen, which he does again and again in the Book of Revelation.
He's doing, as a same kind of idea when they open the the abyss, there's lots of lots of
imagery over and over again in the different cycles of the Book of Revelation of this. But that,
at the end, as we're approaching the final judgment, right, when things will finally all be set right,
when justice will finally prevail, that as the time of God's
of God's patience.
comes to an end in favor of justice, that there will be this kind of final unleashing of these powers,
right, where God will remove the restraints, remove sort of the protection that we've had from the consequences of our own actions.
Up to that point, there's this final unleashing, and that's to bring about a great final repentance before the end, right?
Right. This is
of the last shot. Right? So the reason why the scriptures are getting again, portray things is
getting really, really bad right before the end, is that God intends things getting really, really bad
to be this last final call to repentance. Before it's too late because it's the repentance that he
wants to see. And it's because it's the repentance that he wants to see that we see with the
the four horsemen, even with the four horsemen of the
apocalypse, there are still limits. Yeah. It's still only a
portion of the earth that's subjected to them more than ever
before, but still within limits. Because the goal is still
to bring the wicked to repentance not to destroy them. Yeah.
All right. Well, that wraps up the second half of this
episode of the Lord of Spirits. But we've got a third half
because as we like to say, or as I like to say anyway, it's a
showing to half so we'll be right back.
After this, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Arise of God, the Gospel of Christ's defeat of demons,
sin and death, written by Andrew Stephen Damick.
This book is not a sales pitch.
I hope that instead it will be an authentic true proclamation of the gospel.
How or whether you respond to it is important, but I'm not going to make a marketing appeal
to you at the end.
Knowing what the gospel is and being able to teach it to someone else does not require
that you know everything in this book.
But by the end of it, you should know what a gospel is, why there is a gospel at all,
what the gospel is and what the response to it requires.
Arise, O God, the gospel of Christ's defeat
of demons, sin and death.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
2346. Let's 855
AF Radio.
Welcome back.
It's the third half of the World Experience Podcast.
And our state of this episode of the Podcast.
I don't want to make people think that the podcast
is getting close to ending. I don't know.
How long do you think we should make this podcast go, Father?
Hmm.
I don't know.
I haven't thought too much about it.
I've been thinking five years total.
Five years total.
Yeah. I mean, whole Council of God took you 12 and a half years to go all the way through
the Bible, although who knows how long it's going to take the second time around? How old
will you be? I mean, you should be like 60, right? By the time you finish it the next
time, at least. Hypothetically. Now technically, technically, I don't have to go all the way through
this time. That's true. Because ancient faith has from Luke on. I mean, technically, I could
stop at Deuteronomy chapter.
life. And I have a real quick second go right. But I feel like I need to at least go through
the end of the gospel of Mark. Yeah. Just to use up as much of ancient faiths, hard drive
space and bandwidth as I pass. You know, the thing is, is a hard drive space is really a
dime a dozen these days. You know, a dime for a dozen what? I don't know. But you don't
need those scales from famine to make this work out.
Okay. Well, it cost me a whole days wage for one episode of whole
And now that you said what you said, all these people like, oh,
there's only two years left. Two years left to the podcast. Who knows?
We'll see. It could be could be. You run out of stuff to say.
Can just retire. He got told it's gone. That's right. Exactly.
They've paradise put it in a parking lot.
We could do like, you know, we can also loop around and, you know, do, you
know, angels and demons, Redux and, and you know, even bigger and
We got her.
We recorded the old episodes.
Yeah.
can actually hear everything with less less Mexican radio and and such. I don't feel like that would
be an improvement though. No, I mean, I feel like people need to have a warm fuzzy feeling about
the Mexican radio by this point. Yes. I miss it frankly. Yeah. Last. I grew up in Southern California.
I always felt at home. Mm-hmm. They'll sit tones. Yeah. Wilting through my ungrounded electronics.
Well, we are
talking about the bad boys, the apocalypse this time around.
We've gone through the four horsemen of the apocalypse.
But wait, there's more.
They're not the only baddies at the end.
And as we've seen, it varies other points
in the scripture too.
It's not like the four horsemen show up
for the first time, even with all that,
bam, going on there in Revelation 6.
They do show up at other points.
But there's other figures that we wanted to discuss too.
And
And for those of you who are fans of the late great planet Earth by Mr. Hal Inzi,
you might be familiar with Gog and Megag.
And that's what we're going to be talking about now with some other stuff.
Mostly Gog.
And also a little bit of Megag.
Yes.
Not just Gog.
Now they relate to Kingdom Come.
Exactly.
The Kingdom Come.
So.
All right.
Where should we start?
Well, we should, I was about to say we should begin at the beginning, but actually we're
not.
No.
Yes, as much as I like making that joke, both Rodgers and Hammer Steining.
And I'm just gonna make every one's day would do a verb now.
Here we go.
to we're actually going to start with the main biblical passage.
that talks about Gog, Magog, at all.
They're not the world of Gog, or Mr. Gog's,
but Gog and Magog at least.
That's Zechial chapter 38.
Okay, so I'm gonna read a bunch to you all
to just listen, and we're gonna talk about bits of it.
Story time with Father Henry.
Yeah, yeah. Starting in the verse 1,
The word of the Lord came to me.
Son of man, set you...
face toward Gog of the land of Megag, the chief prince of Misek in Tubaal and
prophesy against him and say, thus says the Lord God, behold, I am against you, O Gog,
chief prince of Misek and Tubaal, and I will turn you about and put hooks into
your jaws, and I will bring you out and all your army, horses and horsemen, all of
them clothed in full armor, a great host, all of them with buckler and shield
wielding swords, Persia, Kush, and Putt are with them, all of them with shield and
helmet.
Gomer and all his words, Beth Togarmoff, from the uttermost parts of the north with all his
words, many peoples are with you.
Be ready and keep ready.
You and all your hosts that are assembled about you and be a guard for them.
After many days you will be mustard.
In the latter years you will go against the land that has restored from more the land
whose people were gathered from many peoples upon the mountains of Israel, which had been
a continual waste.
Its people were brought out from the peoples and now dwell securely all of them.
You will advance.
coming on like a storm, you will be like a cloud covering the land you and all
your hordes and many peoples with you. Thus says the Lord God on that day thoughts
will come into your mind and you will devise an evil scheme and say, I will go
up against the land of unwalled villages. I will fall upon the quiet people who
dwell securely all of them dwelling without walls and having no bars or gates. To
seize spoil and carry off plunder, to turn your hand against the waste places that
that are now inhabited.
and the people who are gathered from the nations
who have acquired livestock and goods
who dwell at the center of the earth.
Shiba and Didan and the merchants of Tarsation,
all its leaders will say to you,
have you come to see spoil,
have you assembled your hosts to carry off plunder,
to carry away silver and gold,
to take away livestock and goods,
to seize great spoil?
Therefore, son of man prophesy and say to God,
thus says the Lord God.
On that day when my people Israel are dwelling securely,
will you not know it?
You will come.
come from your place out of the uttermost parts of the North.
You and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great host, a mighty army.
You will come up against my people Israel like a cloud covering the land.
In the latter day I will bring you against my land that the nations may know me.
When through you, O Gog, I vindicate my holiness before their eyes.
Thus says the Lord God.
Are you he of whom I spoke in former days by my servants the prophets of Israel, who in
those days prophets
side for years that I would bring you against them. But on that day, the day that
God shall come against the land of Israel declares the Lord God, my wrath will
be roused in my anger. For in my jealousy and in my blazing wrath I declare, on
that day there should be a great earthquake in the land of Israel, the fish of
the sea and the birds of the heavens and the beasts of the field and all, creeping
things that creep on the ground, and all the people who are on the face of the
earth shall quake at my presence. And the mountains shall be thrown down and the
clips so far and
every wall shall tumble to the ground.
I will summon a sword against Gog on all my mountains that clears the Lord God.
Every man's sword will be against his brother.
With pestilence and bloodshed, I will enter into judgment with him, and I will reen upon
him in his hordes, and the many peoples who are with him torrential reens and hylestones,
fire and sulfur.
So I will show my greatness and my holiness, and make myself known in the eyes of many nations.
and they will know that I am the Lord.
It's like a pulp fiction ending there.
Well, remember, this is one of the places where we would be helped by translating it
is then they will know that I am Yahweh.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So, one of the first things people might have noticed right off the jump is that in Ezekiel,
dog and mage are not like two dudes.
like, Gog is from Magog.
Yeah.
It's a person from a place.
Gog is a person and Magog is a place.
So it's not clear exactly when people started saying Gog and Magog.
But we find it in some of the Dead Sea Scrolls.
We find it in some other second temple literature.
And so that was already an established usage by the time and we're going to get to it in
the Book of Revelation, when St. John refers to Gog and Magi.
that end had already been around for a couple of centuries.
Although it's unclear exactly how that.
So even though Magog is the place where he's from,
Gog is the leader of this whole coalition of nations.
Right. And that coalition of nations, it's not like a group of
that are next to each other.
Because it includes Kush and Put,
which are African nations,
it includes Persia, right?
It includes Gomer, right?
And these are all different directions from Israel.
And the conquest that's talked about goes as far as like Tarshish,
Tartar Shares Switches.
is in what's now Spain.
And Shiba and Dadaan, which is down at the end of the Arabian Peninsula, right?
So recovering all the compass directions, right?
Like sort of the whole known world is involved with this.
Even though Daga's armies are said to come from the North, which is one of the things that
indicates to us that this is the sacred geography direction north, right?
Yeah, that's what we were.
where the bad guys are.
Yeah, rather than being literal, from the literal north, because of course Persia is not north of Israel.
Yeah, and those African nations are kind of well-
Libya is not north of Israel.
Yeah, western, south-ish.
So, yeah.
So, there is even within this, right?
that people should take even
a lot of modern people haven't taken them. This is not just talking, not intended to be
literally referring to a particular king at the time of Ezekiel who had actually put together
this precise coalition, et cetera, et cetera. Right. And in the response, and God's response,
in his judgment, you see that God responds by unleashing.
demonic powers like the ones we were just talking about. Like at verse 21 when God says,
I will summon a sword against a god on all my mountains, right? Then he's sort of unleashing
these demonic powers on god himself, right? As a response to justice against gods in justice.
So, it's trying to work out who exactly...
is and where exactly magog is, right?
From people who take you the approach of,
we need to match this up to a place or just,
hey, let's look at the other places
where these terms are used in scripture, right?
Try to understand how these things connect.
The main place where magog is referenced in scripture
other than this is in Genesis chapter 10
and the table of nations.
Yeah, when you got all those big lists
of all the descendants of Noah.
the sentence of his three sons. Right. And God is, or sorry, not God, Magog is one of the
sons of Japheth. So this is a grandson of Noah. Right. And Japheth, we talked about before,
is sort of the father of the Indo-Europeans. And so those nations get grouped under there.
that doesn't boil it down a ton.
Yeah, right. And I mean, and some of these other sons of J fifth like in Genesis 10 to you got Gomer
Magog, Maddai, Javan, Tubaal, Meshek, and you're right. These are some of these other
other sons of J fifth that are that are mentioned in that list of those that
God has coming with him from Ezekiel. Right. Right. So it's sort of a sampler platter of
Grants of no right that's obviously going back along
way, right? The, and, you know, I think, I think that it would be taking it too
literally to just say, oh, it's just referencing like the Indo-Europeans. Because you also have
push yeah and put
a list who are not Indo-Europeans.
Right.
So you can't even boil it down to that
if you try to be literal.
So Megog, if you try to attack it edamologically, right?
The best folks have come up with so far, shall we say,
is that this is from the Assyrian matgoogu.
Okay.
Which means the land of Goo Goo.
Or that would mean Magog leads the land of Gog.
Right.
Gog from the land of Gog.
I'm always having that.
So that's not super helpful.
Yeah, like from the land of,
like I'm always hearing like the land of Oz
from the land of anyway.
Yes.
I am Father Stephen from the house of Father Stephen.
Right?
So yeah, that didn't help so much.
And so in trying to figure out what the Gog in Magog and Gog would be referring to, the
best, and I think still pretty unconvincing argument that people have come up with is
that it might be referring to Gaiji's, who was the first sort of imperial king of Lydia.
There were kings of Lydia before him in Asia Minor.
but he was the first one to really sort of.
become a world stage player.
It's start to expand his territory.
That was in the seventh century BC.
So we're about a century before Ezekiel.
Okay.
So it's not impossible.
But obviously, he can't be referring to that person as historical person
because he's dead. Right.
So even in that kind of context, even if...
the name is coming from from
Gai G's. Then you have to say,
well, Gai G's is being used as
sort of a type, right?
It's sort of an image of
something else, right?
So it's obviously Ezekiel
wouldn't have to pronounce the
doom of somebody already dead.
So Lydia, probably the thing
Lydia's the most.
famous for is they invented money. They invented like coins as a means of exchange.
There's also some musical modes. There's the Lydian mode and hypolydian mode, I think
it's a mix of Lydian. I don't know. Yeah. There's a team, people call in and correct me.
they had their own language.
Yes.
This is a switch was distinct from
Louisville and Hittite.
Yeah, an ancient, now completely lost into European language that was mostly dead by
first century BC, even.
Yeah.
But Guy G's name was actually Kukos.
In Lidian.
Yeah.
But here's the thing, and I haven't told Father Andrew this yet, because I was saving
this for him.
This Guy G's the King of Lidia.
Bye.
is the gui-jis of the ring of gui-jis.
Okay.
The ring and play-dose republic that makes people invisible.
Oh, that's right.
Which means gui-jis,
if he is Gogh from Agog,
is the historical saueron.
Oh, I was gonna say it was the historical golem, but okay.
No.
Because, you know, there's a gun at the beginning, right?
So yeah.
And, you know, in the habit, all that we know about that ring is that makes people invisible.
Yeah.
So.
That's true.
I'm just saying.
No, I am just saying.
He's all.
Well, all right.
Yes.
throwing a bone to Eugene up there in Minnesota.
Yes, exactly. He is freaking out right now. I do it.
I told you guys.
Yes.
He also went a great victory against the Samarians, C-I-M-M-E-R-I-A-N.
So we've got Conan, we've got Lord of the Rings,
Ice, all centered around Gog.
Anyway.
Oh, Gog.
Oh, the time.
The other place where either those words occurs in scripture
is it?
first Chronicles 5 verse 4, there's a Gog or a Goog depending on how you read the Hebrew.
Who's a descendant of Ruben.
And therefore not the guy we're talking about.
Yeah.
Because he was an Israelite.
not related as man-god.
by the way. Oh, which may have been Stanley misspelling some magog. Nice.
Man, God is the souls of a billion people killed by Odin, given monstrous
form, come to kill the Norse gods. But not unrelated to the bloods we
talked about in half to. Yeah. So the best we could do to
to boil that down.
the best we could do in terms of trying to assign this to a historical personage who
Ezekiel might have been addressing is to say, well, he might have been using
Gaiji's, this King Gaiji's as a type, right? As a representative of this Gauk person.
Sort of the way we talked about the Antichrist episode.
When we talked about how you have Antichrist, right? You have individual people like Nero,
who are sort of an image of.
right this, a representative of this, but you can't get Ezekiel's prophecy to be addressing the historical
guide G's because it doesn't work out chronology, right? Now when you get into the earliest known
interpretation of this. Right of who who the
this gorg is. Right. So now we've talked about other places where it's
show up in the scriptures. Outside the Hebrew scriptures, the earliest
interpretation we get is actually since we're talking about a prophecy of
Ezekiel, Ezekiel's living during the exile. So in the middle of the six
century BC, the earliest interpretation of this that we get isn't in
second
Jewish literature, it's in the Greek translations of the Hebrew Scriptures.
Yeah, there's some interesting variations. So this is and this is critically important.
The Greek Old Testament tradition is second-templed Jewish literature. Yeah. Yeah.
Because every translation is an interpretation. Right.
So effectively a translation is a commentary.
automatically. It's true right. It's no way around to have to make choices right. And so our earliest
commentary are various Greek passages, some of which refer to Gog in the Greek tradition that don't
at least obviously in the Hebrew, the original Hebrew. And what that shows us is that the person
translating.
them into Greek was aware of traditions concerning Gog who Gog was that existed at the time that
the Greek was being translated and considered those to be the correct way of reading
and interpreting the text. These translers didn't sit down and decide I'm going to change
this text. They were reading it and translating it, but in between reading it and translating
You can get on...
are, is the culture they grew up in, the cultural
understandings they had, what they were taught religiously,
what they believed religiously, that all form a filter
through which the text was passing, right?
On the way from their eyes to their pen, right?
And so we see Gog stuff existed between those two places
and then end up on the page at the other end of the pen
part of the analogy.
Yeah.
and the NNNNNNNNNNN NNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNBN
Greek translation. And the biggest one of those is in Amos chapter 7 verse 1.
Yeah, and this is the, this is the kind of thing that y'all, you only notice it if you actually
sit down and compare these things, you know, you look at what it says in the, even in translations,
you know, a translation of the Hebrew and a translation of the Greek, and you start to notice
like, wait a minute, this is not just like synonyms or whatever, but there are other words here
that are not a-
other one, or there's some words that are not in the later version that are in the
early one. And that's what this case, like so if you look at a translation of the Hebrew
of Amos 7-1, it's a longer verse than the Greek translation from the BC period. So yeah,
Amos 7-1, so first I'm going to read the ESV. So this is looking at Hebrew texts and translating
them. This is what the Lord God showed me. Behold, he was
forming locusts when the latter growth was just beginning to sprout and behold it was the latter
growth after the king's mohings. Kings mohings, I mean it feels like there should be the name of some
sort of British neighborhood. Oh I live at King's mohings. Yeah or the name of a landscaping business.
Hey, that's right.
Yeah, so the Greek ends this way.
A swarm of locusts.
coming early and behold one Locust, Gog the King. And in Greek it's Ithoo, Vrukos is Glog,
O Vassilefs. So pretty straightforward. Behold a Locust and it's Gog the King. And for all of you vampire
people out there, or vampire interested people, I hope you're not vampire people. Vampire interested people.
the word vrujos meaning locust.
It comes from the Greek verb, vrico, vrico, which means to eat greedily.
And we all remember the vrico lacas from one of our Halloween episodes. So there you go.
There you go. I'm not saying that locusts are vampires. I'm saying that they both have this word
for eating greedily. I think you may have accidentally offended the vamp curious,
so much. But are they sparking out empires?
the beginning of the verse in Greek is the same.
This is what the Lord God showed me, behold, a swarm of locusts coming early and behold
one locust, God the King, right?
Yeah, so there's no way to get that out of the Hebrew.
Yeah.
You can go look at the Hebrew.
It's not translation Hebrew.
Sometimes there are places where the Hebrew and Greek differ.
And if you know both languages, you could call...
look at the he especially the Hebrew you can look at the Hebrew would be like oh well they read that this way right you like you could tell
right or they this word could mean two different things they
chose this other one right you can find a lot of those things
heck i'll give an example the uh there's a place in the book of Jonah where uh in the Hebrew
Uh...
when the guys on the boat in the storm ask Jonah who he is, he says, I am a Hebrew,
right, which is Yvri in Hebrew.
That's how you say Hebrew in Hebrew.
Yvri.
And if you look at the Greek there, they ask him who he is.
that says that he is
the most secure you, servant of the Lord.
Yeah.
Those don't look like it all,
unless you know that Evry
and Evid, right, Evid is servant or slave in Hebrew.
Evid, yeah.
Look almost identical in Hebrew.
if you don't have vowels.
The only real difference is that
translating it as Hebrew means that you see a race there
in our sound.
And translating it as Servant of the Lord means you saw a
dollar there, which makes a desound.
And the difference between a race and a dollar in Hebrew
is literally a little tiny leg sticking out.
of one letter. Right. So it is there aren't two letters that close to each other in English
that I could use it as an example. Right. It's like a tiny little piece. So you can figure it out
right? But there is no figuring out
Amos 7 verse 1.
Yeah. It's...
The word, the word, God is, God the King is, yeah, it's just not in there.
God is not in there.
Yeah.
You have the King's moans.
You have King in there, right?
Right.
But God is just inserted, right?
I am a guest and a God that they would insert that word.
As the King of the Locus, right?
Which would be the only way that can get in there is if it was sort of common
knowledge to the translator that
oh,
is talking about Gog. Why would he think this is talking about Gog? Right? Well, there are some
other places, right? So remember, Amos is what we call in English Bible usually one of the minor
prophets. And historically, Amos is part of the book of the 12. What we call the minor prophets
are 12 books, 12 short prophetic books that were all on one scroll.
Yeah, right.
And we're considered to be one book.
And we're commented on by, for example, Church Fathers as one book.
So we have like St. Jerome's commentary on the 12.
And he goes through all of them, right?
Because they're all seen as one book.
book. And so Amos is one of those books on the same scroll.
right next to it on the scroll is the book of Joel, right? Meaning the guy who's
translating Amos in degree also translated Joel in degree. Okay, so he's no doubt
familiar with the text of Joel 2 verses 20 through 25, which refer to
to, at verse 20, it refers to God driving away the armies of the North.
Yep.
And in verse 25, it...
refers to God driving away the locusts.
There you go.
The locusts are the same language.
So there is this idea of a locust army that comes from the north.
Where does God come from?
With his big army, the north, right?
And so the translator is reflecting in Amos 7 verse 1 in the Greek translation,
this tradition of understand of of Gog's locust army from the North.
right, which is how these prophetic texts were being interpreted at the time he did the translation.
But there's another interesting thing that shows up in some of the Greek texts of the Old Testament
that associates Gog with something a little different. And one of these is in the Greek translation
of numbers 24, verse 7.
Yeah, and this is a case where it switches one name for another.
name, although admittedly they're kind of similar names.
Yes, a little bit.
Yes.
More similar in Hebrew than in Greek.
Yeah.
Excuse me.
So this is from this passage in Numbers, is the middle of pretty sure if I'm wrong,
correctly, Balum's second oracle.
I know we've talked about this on the show before this episode where
or Balom, son of Bior, Moabite, Fokiro gets hired to curse Israel, and instead he keeps
blessing Israel and cursing Israel's enemies.
And so in the second one, in the middle of it, there is a reference where it's talking
about the Messiah who's going to come from Israel and how great his kingdom is going
to be. And it says that his kingdom is going to be greater than the
to have Ag Ag. Okay.
Which G.A.G.
Isn't, you know, for fans of the Book of Esther.
Yes. Ag Ag Ag.
Yeah. The big bad guy in that one,
Heyman, is an Ag Ag Ag.
So he's from that group.
Right.
And Ag Ag was the king who, the Amalakite king,
who's always supposed to kill, but then.
Yeah.
So, this is...
Ag Ag there's a reference to the amulakites to probably the preeminent of the giant clans,
right? Sort of the worst of the giant clans or the example of the giant clans. This is the
most well-known king, aside from Amalek himself, of the Amulakites. And if there's any doubt in
your mind that it's talking about the Amulakites, if you go a few verses later in the same prophecy by
I bail him. He goes straight to talking about the
amulakites. So he's very clearly thinking amulakite when he mentions agach. However, the Greek has
Gog instead of agach. So kind of putting him in the, this guy is kind of a giant sort of category.
Yes. Right. So this is a change that's showing us that right by the time you get to
the translation in degree.
right of the Torah, right? The Amalakites, the literal Amalakites, right? The literal Ag Ag is sort
of old news, right? And at that point, Gog is the one who's seen as sort of this anti-Besiah,
anti-God figure, king figure, of the nations.
of the world. And similarly, Codex Vaticanus, which is one of the oldest, mostly complete
biblical manuscripts that we have, along with Codex Sanéaticus.
Codex Vaticanus, of course, the Old Testament is in Greek. I say, of course, people may not realize
that. Both side of the edicus and
Vaticanus are Greek Bibles,
old and New Testament.
And so in Vaticanus in particular, when you go to, which is mainly is one manuscript, but also one of the oldest ones we have, when you go by a lot, when you go to Deuteronomy 3 verses 1 and 13,
instead of talking about Ogg, King of Bashan, it has Gog, King of Bashan, which...
mean someone could say, well, that's just a mistake in that case.
It's just one letter of difference.
But like scribal mistakes is a whole realm of study.
Super obscure and nitty, but like this is, yeah, yeah, I've,
why would he think it was God?
Well, because God at that time, at that time had come to occupy the kind of place.
and even though I don't like this.
use of the word in the Christian imaginary that it previously
been held by awking of Pasha.
Yeah.
And even if it is like a mistake, it's a different,
it's an unusual kind of scribal mistake.
Number one, twice, right?
Had a letter.
Yeah, to add a letter.
Usually, like, you scribal mistakes,
people leave a letter out, or they get the wrong letter,
or they leave a word out.
or something like that.
I mean, this is the kind of thing
that if you're copying a text,
these are the kinds of mistakes
that people make.
But to add a letter is a little bit,
a lot rarer.
We'll just put it that way.
But either way, even if it's a-
There are some manuscripts where it has
August instead of Gog, the other way.
Yeah.
But those are more understandable.
You dropped a letter, right?
Yeah.
Exactly.
And they didn't notice it because
is a guy, right? Like yeah. Bye.
right? So, but so that shows you in the tax. This gives us an idea. Even if you say it's a mistake,
why this mistake? Yes, exactly. Right. Why add a Yama? Why not add, you know, a beta?
Bug king of Bashar Adelta, right? Like if you're going to add a letter, right?
So it shows what's going on in the minds of the folks, right?
against now moving beyond. I was just going to say if you added a rough breathing mark
instead, he could be the original boss hog. Just put that out there. They weren't being
pronounced. They weren't being pronounced. Oh, come on. You're ruining my dukes of hazard
joke. I know. I know. Dang it. Boss Hogg I'm pretty sure was based on Texas
governor Jim Hawk.
who did indeed name one of his daughters, Ima.
Wow.
Wow, man.
At a pure hate despite.
Wow.
So going outside of the text, right, and its translations.
Places where we find people referring
to Gog and or Magog, right?
Sort of now outside of the scriptures themselves.
Josephus refers to Magog.
He's referring to Magog in the context of Genesis 10.
He never mentions Gog.
But in the context of the Table of Nations in Genesis 10,
he identifies Magog as the Scythians,
which would be roughly part of Romania.
Oh boy.
And he also has Joseph
Josephus also has a story, not, he does, Josephus does not relate this to Magog, but also in Josephus,
he has a story about Alexander the Great having an iron gate that he built to hold back a particular
tribe of Scythians. Not in the context of Magog being the Scythians, right? In two different places.
the reason I bring that up though is
that when you get a little later, well, a lot later in this case, the Syriac legend of Alexander
the Great. Now you have this sort of full blown tradition that Alexander made this gate
and put spells and magic whammy on it to hold back Gog and Magog.
Yeah. Yeah, I mean, a lot of people love Alexander the Great, but should also remember
that
he had quite the religious career.
You know, he was making himself a God king,
Pharaoh, you know, doing magical spells.
I mean, he's deep into all that demon stuff.
Big time.
Yes.
But yeah, so this and the Syracalegic of Alexander's
from the early to mid seventh century, AD.
Yeah.
But so there is this magic gate, right, the likes,
But you
You can see how Josephus had a couple stories that probably ended up becoming the building
blocks, right, of the bigger story, more developed story later on.
Sudo-Mathodius, a little later in the seventh century, tells a version of the story where
he adds this element where, right, well, this gate, like what's it attached to, right?
So you can see how these things could develop, right?
You've got to kind of then explain, so the story gets elaborated a little more to explain
things.
And he has the gate being between these two mountains.
Are these the bronze mountains?
These are the bronze mountains of the North.
Yeah.
That we read about in Zagariah.
But in Sino-Mathodias, the two mountains
like sort of help out.
Because they, I guess, don't like Gaga Megagi either.
And they kind of move closer together.
So I have to just put up a gate.
so they could...
they could just get gated off.
A magical.
But here, one of the things you see
with this whole gate language too, though,
is remember what we talked about
with the Four Horsemen being kind of unleashed,
right, into the world.
The idea here is that Gog and Magog
are kind of cooped up behind this gate
until the end when the gate's gonna get thrown open
and they're gonna get to go poo-koo, right?
So there's the restry.
image again. Yeah. Yeah. When you get into later Greek versions after pseudo-mathodias,
the element that gets added to this story is that Gog and Magog, these folks are all cannibals.
Man, straight first. It said that they'd just eat corpses and babies,
which I don't know if that was trying to be like less harsh about cannibalism or not,
but then they just went full on to just the cannibals.
There were was...
They're all werewolves right well as you get a giant element here too again. Yes right right
And this whole story about Alexander building the gate with Gog and and Magog behind it
Actually ends up in the Quran
Yeah, and one fun thing that I discovered during our prep for this episode
Is that there are some Muslim commentators
who identify Gog and Megog as...
the Vikings. So that's great. Yeah. The Vikings. Right. So you have this full-blown sort of story by
the seventh century. Yeah, that doesn't just go away. Right. In the West, obviously, they lose most
of their contact with the East. But the story sticks around. The story still shows up at these
illuminated manuscripts of the Middle Ages and in universal histories and stuff.
And it still arrived to the point that when Marco Polo went to China and first saw a part
of the Great Wall, he declared that he had discovered the gate.
Nice.
Right.
He said, this must be the wall of these.
Where's the gate?
Show me where the gate is, where Gog and Bagog are behind it.
Wow.
So it was sort of that firmly set.
So you have that tradition, but then you also have sort of like we saw with the the
anti-Christ.
You see all through sort of Christian history, everybody I don't like is literally
Gog.
Right.
So you find a lot of early Christian writings before Christianity is legal where Rome is
the back dog of the Emperor's cock.
Yeah, I mean, it's sort of like how now, you know, on the internet, everyone.
you don't like his Hitler. Yes, exactly. Yes. And so St. Ambrose, you could find saying that the Goths
were bagogged. When the Mongols invaded the Mongolian invasion happened, they were
or Magog. Yeah, I mean, it's this overwhelming horde to go and use a mongolian language. You
know, they're just destroyed.
He's everything in its path.
Right. The Muslim invasions in North Africa, they're literally magog. Right?
Napoleon was identified as being Gog. Yeah, but he is though. Russia.
Well, maybe. But you see this similar kind of thing. Yeah. Right? Yeah.
That there's this idea of this eschatological enemy of God.
Even though you don't get a lot of direct connections between Gog and the Antichrist,
Steven, would you have somebody like Napoleon?
people call both things. You don't
much see the two connected together.
That's interesting.
But it's identified in different ways.
And then, how Lindsay.
How Lindsay.
The mindily cracked the code.
The late, great planet Earth.
One of the literary monuments of the 20th century.
Monument can be used in many different senses.
It's true.
Well, like a baller than a monument really.
It does demarcate something.
That's right.
God bless him.
Yeah, I mean, I grew up with this stuff.
Like, Gog and Megog is the Soviet Union.
Like that was the whole stick.
And the world was going to end 40 years after the establishment of the modern state of
Israel, which means when you and I were about 13 years old.
Yeah, 1988.
I have survived a number of ends of the world.
Yeah.
Right.
But yeah, he has this whole, I mean, it's been a while since I looked at this.
But he has this whole linguistic and garbage,
etymological argument about how he claims that to...
Roch his Russia, Bishak his Moscow.
Yeah, right.
Man.
It just hurts to hear it.
bad etymology. It's just like, it's not just wrong, it's aesthetically offensive.
Yeah. And this, and this wasn't just, I mean, how Lindsay is the one who brings this to
the fore-prope, but this was just considered to be accurate in a lot of the dispensationalist
rule.
Yeah, there are a lot of it.
Still is, frankly, Jack could have been to the day he died would say of that.
Oh, yeah. I mean, there are a lot of people who really believed, you know, that the Russians,
which of course at that point meant the Soviet Union.
and that they are this eschatological enemy of God
and the end of the world is nigh and all this kind of stuff.
Yeah, I mean it's, I always tell people like,
look, if you're gonna identify somebody as Gog and Megog
or if you're gonna identify somebody as the anti-Christ,
you need to have an eschatological exist strategy
for when that person or country
whatever kind of goes off the scene.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh yeah, well didn't stop Jack.
I reject this.
get you know, still KGB and you know, say no one actually did what you're supposed to
do, but look at a profits when it turns out that they were wrong.
Well, I'm not saying anyone should do that to be fair to our pedocostal friends.
They argue that a prophecy is just now way less reliable than it was in the old covenant.
No, they can get the only example of something that got worse and more ineffectual.
Huh?
How about that?
So, yes.
I don't know how that works.
I mean, I really, I can't do better than that, guys.
I love to steal man your argument there,
but it really doesn't make sense to me.
Holy Spirit gets poured out on all flesh.
Save Holy Spirit.
It was in the profits of the Old Testament.
But now everybody could prophesy badly.
We love you.
I have a cost of friends.
Yes.
I just I can't I don't I can't figure out
to steal man it. I can't, I, I, I don't get that hard. It doesn't make sense to me. Dog,
no, not. All right. So there's a big battle at the end, right? It involves Gog and Megog.
Megog. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And this is the other place where Gog and Megog are explicitly mentioned
in Scripture. This is of course the book of Revelation. Yeah. And it's no longer Gog from Megog as it
It isn't Ezekiel.
It's now Gog.
and Megag.
So two figures.
Yeah, so Revelation or?
Well, we'll see.
Yeah, it's true.
It's true.
So Revelation chapter 20, verses 7 through 10.
And when the thousand years are ended,
Satan will be released from his prison
and will come out to deceive the nations
that are at the four corners of the earth,
Gog and Megag to gather them for battle.
Their number is like the sand of the sea.
And they marched up over the broad plane of the earth
surrounded the camp of the
and the beloved city, but fire came down from heaven and consumed them, and the devil,
who had deceived them, was thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur, where the beast and the false
prophet were, and they will be tormented day and night forever and ever.
Yes, so I don't think it's necessarily the case.
I think God can still be a person and Magon can still be a place in what you just read.
Oh, in terms of like...
using the name to designate the people from that place.
Right. So you, well, no, so you have Satan.
Okay. Right.
They go to deceive the nation's plural that are the four corners of the earth.
Oh, sure. Yeah. God and mega.
So God could be referring to Satan and Magog to the nations.
Oh, oh, interesting. Interesting. Yeah. Yeah.
And, and you know, one thing that's notable for me here in this is
It says, and the devil who had deceived them.
Right, so obviously there's two potential sets of them that this could refer to.
There's the saints. Well, he didn't deceive the saints.
They're doing well.
It's, you know, these other nations that have been brought up against the saints,
they're described in this as having been deceived.
They're victims of the devil.
Yes.
So,
is
Well...
And I would say in Revelation there that Gog is actually the prince of this world.
And Magog is, you know, the nations of the world.
So it's still kind of Gog from Magog.
Sure.
But yeah, so this is, we have this kind of final battle.
We've talked before on the show, and I know last time I brought this up, it was a while
back, but people got triggered.
So get ready.
them.
And no, I'm not talking about the fact that your favorite pasta dish is a
damn tortilla cut into strips.
What I am talking about is the pasta thing again, people are going to get
to get scared. Stir the pot. Yes. And there's not pasta in the pot.
Anyway,
that Armageddon
does not refer to the value of Megido.
It's a Greek transliteration of Harmoeid.
Because Moeid, the A there is an Ion.
Right.
Then, Harmoid is the mountain of assembly.
Right? The mountain of God, which is attacked by who in the Old Testament amolec?
Yep.
The amolecites laid siege to the throne of God.
God. And that was that was a Mount Sinai. That was sort of the
ark.
type of that's what made Amalak and the Amalakite sort of the archetypal
enemy even among the giant clans right? And so the imagery that we get in revelation is similar
right that Gog assembles the nations of the world right Persia put right all over the place
right? Gathers them all together to face off against who?
Remember our Greek tradition in Baelum against the Messiah.
and his kingdom, right? The Messiah being the one who rules from the mountain of God.
Right, so this is a parallel there. And so the use and revelation I would argue is another paralleling
of dog from egg dog with this tradition. Right.
And with the giant imagery, right, we can say
Is God here the devil himself? Is it a human sort of motivated and acted on and
through by the devil like say Judas? Is it right? And the answer is yes. Sure, right.
Is this a radically different figure than the Antichrist? No, right? Is this the
final antichrist, I mean kind of, right? So...
In the end, that's who God is.
God is the final enemy of God, gathering and motivating the nations of the world to oppose
and rebel against Him and to attack and seek to destroy His people.
So you could say it is the last and ultimate giant clan.
Huh?
If you're somebody who gets excited about giant.
There are people I've heard in the time of the end. So if you're one of the
Arthanephalum coming back people, this is where I would go if you wanted to
argue yes. That's something like that would happen again at the end. That's how
bad it would get. This is where I go. Yeah.
Well, to wrap up this episode, this eschatologic...
episode of the Lord of Spirits. One of the questions that I think is paramount, really. I guess the main
thing we should be asking, as we look at the scriptures, as we read the teachings of the fathers,
as we listen to experience and participate in the divine services and so on and so on,
What is the purpose of this within the Christian life?
Right. I know a lot of people had a lot of anticipation for this episode of our listeners
and even for other parts of this series. You know, because it's really, I mean, it's
some very interesting stuff, right? It's really just intellectually stimulating, you know,
the floor horsemen, the anti-Christ, all this kind of stuff. It's very, very intriguing.
And it's good to be intellectually stimulated and to be intrigued and to be interested and
to want to know and to understand and explore and play with and all that kind of stuff.
But again, the point is why is this given for us?
The scriptures are not written for our intellectual curiosity, even though I'm a big believer in
intellectual curiosity.
They're not written for that purpose.
In the tradition of the Church, in general,
is not given to us for that purpose.
It's given to us.
All these things are given to us so that we might believe
that Jesus is the Christ and that believing in Him,
we might have life in His name to use the words
of the Apostle and Evangelist John.
So then, what do all of these bad guys of the apocalypse?
Right, the forehorseman, Gog and Megog.
And of course, the accompanying swarms of locusts, what does that mean for us in particular?
You know, it's not just about being right or wrong about these things or having a colorful
depiction of the end.
It's about what do we do with that?
And I think there's a number of things that we could say about that.
One of the themes that we've talked about a number of times on the podcast is this theme
of what we call the left hand of God.
to use some of the language you see in the books of kings,
where there's the elect, the obedient angels at the right hand of God,
and then the disobedient at the left hand, meaning the demons,
and how they, while they do their own will, they end up doing God's will.
And we talked about that a bunch of times in this episode,
especially that the four horsemen and these other demonic figures are kind of on the leash,
on a leash and sometimes they are
unleashed, let go, having ben restrained, but under limits and then brought back that kind of thing.
And I mean, it is quite simply so that we might repent. Part of the Genesis this podcast some
three years ago was when Father Stephen and I appeared on Father Tom's Roku show, ancient faith
Today, live, and the question was asked, is the pandemic judgment?
from God, right?
And of course, we both said yes it is,
meaning that judgment is God establishing his justice.
And so the pandemic was an opportunity for us to repent.
And of course, you know, Reshif, right?
This pestilence God is one of the four horsemen
involved in any kind of mass outbreak of disease.
So there is on that
love.
right, suffering and so forth is an opportunity for us to repent.
Both in our personal lives, right, our own individual personal lives, like my
participation in the divine services, in prayer, in omnisgiving, in active love,
in self-sacrifice, all that kind of stuff, but also on the larger scale of,
Okay, how am I helping?
make the world a more beautiful, more just, better, kinder place. Like, what am I doing
to help address the ills of the world? What am I doing to make things right? And it doesn't
matter if I was the one who made them wrong or not. If I can, if I, you know, if I see
someone near me suffering, it doesn't matter if I'm the one who caused the suffering. Now
I might well have been.
Might be deliberately.
Maybe.
through neglect, who knows? Maybe just the fact that I'm a sinner has this
spiritual effect. But repentance we can repent on our own behalf in terms of
putting our own souls right, but also repent on behalf of the world in which we
live, putting the world right. And I'm not talking about, you know, like I am out
there to change the world kind of stuff, which I don't know what anybody
means by that anymore. I'm going to make a difference. Whatever.
Okay, it's not bad language.
I'm just not sure what it's supposed to mean now,
but you can make things better where you are.
You can serve the people near you,
whether it's your family, your friends,
or your coworkers, or your fellow parishioners.
I mean, parish really should be doing this
for the parish and for anyone who comes to the parish, right?
But also there's another side to this,
which is, I can might ask, well, okay.
God's unleashing demons again.
He's letting them do, like God is not doing evil things,
but he's allowing, he's removing his protection
from these evil spirits doing their evil things.
What about people who seem to be suffering unjustly?
You know, is God saying, you're bad,
and so you need to shape up.
I mean, we've all, I'm sure, seen or at least heard of
some unjust suffering.
Right, whether it's mass disease, invasion,
you know, individual people suffering from health
serious health problems or other kinds of suffering in their life, you know, whatever it might be.
Why do these things happen? Is God, you know, is God smacking them down? Is God telling them you're bad?
You know, so get better, right?
Right? Not necessarily. I mean it might be. It might be.
But not necessarily. We all remember, and I think we've mentioned this on the podcast before, but
it is worth repeating. St. Paul talks about having been sent an angel of Satan, a messenger of
Satan, is often gets translated, but a demon that tormented him. We don't know exactly
what experience he was having that he described in that way. There's various ideas about that.
But he is the one who's
said that it was this evil spirit. And he asked God three times, take it away, and God says,
no, my grace is sufficient for you. Why would God do that? It was Saint Paul, this unrighteous
evil man that needed this in order to shape up? No. He's a righteous man, certainly by this point.
One of the whole these people ever lived. But the experience that he had was so that he might gain
even more of the great
of God. As God said, my grace is sufficient for you, so that he might advance even more
in holiness because repentance is not only to undo some bad thing that you did, or even
that someone else did. That certainly is included in repentance. But it is also to undo
any imperfection. It is also to advance towards being
more like Christ to become more worthy of being adopted as sons of God.
Right?
So there is an advancement.
Repentance is not just to set things back to zero.
It's actually to move positively above that, to grow past that.
Right?
And the experiences of suffering, demonic suffering, that we have are an opportunity for that.
we are tempted and I understandably so to say why.
God, why? He even Job said, why God, why? Right? He was able to do that without
sinning, which super hard for me. I don't think I could manage it. But one of
the answers to why God, why? I'm not saying it's the only one. I'm speaking in
general, not in particular, but in general, one of the answers is so that I
I might have an opportunity to become a whole year.
You know, it's not only...
to deal with some sin. It is also to advance in holiness. And so when we consider this
rogue's gallery of demonic bad guys at the end, this is how we should receive this. Not
to say, oh, that's cool and weird and whatever scary. But like, okay, these things are put
in front of me so that I...
may learn repentance even more, or maybe start, or maybe restart, whatever is applicable
for me.
So that's one way that I'm receiving what we talked about tonight.
So I want to build a little off of what Father Andrew was just talking about.
you
He was talking about sort of
Rappling our intellect around
the shape of life in the world as we live in it and
finding meaning and
growing and holiness. I want to focus on the fact that
you can choose to be invincible
You can choose.
to live your life in a way where no one will ever be able to hurt you. Let alone do
any harm to you. Let alone damage you. This isn't like a one-time choice that you
make. Like okay, yeah, that sounds good. I'll choose that. This is something that we
We have to practice choosing over and over and over again.
And the way it works is revealed in some of the stories in Scripture and things that we talked about in this episode.
One of the examples we used is we read a little piece of sort of the deliberations among Joseph's brothers when they were trying to decide whether to kill him or just thrown out a well and ultimately to sell him into slavery in Egypt.
end of that story, of course, when they realize that their brothers alive, that their brother
now has the power of life and death over them in Egypt, they're terrified. And rightfully so.
And Joseph says to them, you meant it to be for evil, but God meant it for good. And by that,
he means they were trying to do evil to their brother Joseph but God had brought good out of it.
God had put Joseph into the position to be able to save the lives of his whole family
through it.
And that dynamic is at the core, of course, of what we've been talking about tonight
with these demonic spiritual powers who mean only evil for us.
Don't make that mistake.
They only want to destroy humanity.
They only want to do us harm.
but who got a l-
to at sometimes and in some places to try to do some of that harm in order that he can bring
good out of it. And one of the chief ways is his father, Andrew, said through inspiring
repentance. But choosing how we're going to receive things and what we're going to do with them
is a freedom that we have in Christ. When we are slaves to sin,
Orthodox Church, we commonly call the sins passions because they make us passive.
They take control of us.
So greed takes control of you, anger takes control of you, lust takes control of you,
laziness takes control of you, pride takes control of you.
All of these things, once they get control of you, will cause you to do things, then in
another moment on another day at another time you would have thought were unthinkable.
but whether you're the grip of sin you...
you start doing them. And so when we're bound by sin, we're not free. But when Christ has
set us free from sin, we now have freedom not to just react. We have freedom not to just
be passive. We're free to always and at every moment to be active in the world. And so that
That means when someone...
Just outright insults me.
Right.
Not remotely trying to offer a morsel of constructive criticism.
Just outright insults me.
Says things designed to hurt me.
I have a choice to make.
I could choose to give into anger.
I can choose to retaliate.
I could choose to receive that insult.
and have it foster humility in me.
When someone offers me something that maybe sideways could be taken as constructive criticism,
I can make the choice to receive it as constructive criticism,
regardless of how it was intended. I can use it to improve.
I can use it to repent or to change or to work harder,
or to see something I didn't see before,
about myself or about the people around me.
or to make something right that I've done wrong.
These things can bring me to repentance.
These things can increase my patience and my resolve.
When I get sick, I can use that too.
It's funny how often I pray when I'm sick to be healthy again
and how little I pray to thank God that I'm healthy when I'm healthy.
I can use it to help me understand my own weakness and dependence on others.
and then some others.
I can use it to develop empathy for other people who are suffering the same things.
That's true even for the most horrible thing that could possibly happen to me.
Whatever that thing would be, it's happened to other people and is happening to other people.
Other people who need compassion and who need empathy and who need someone to help them
through those difficulties.
If we become consistent in making those choices, we become invincible.
No one can harm us, no one can hurt us.
Whatever anyone does to us no matter how evil, no matter how motivated by evil, ends up
working to our good.
Up to and including if we're ready to die, if we're ready to die because we've been living
our life following Christ, they can't even do us harm by murdering us.
You can become invulnerable to harm if we start to practice these things.
But this isn't how we've been taught to live our lives, and it isn't how we've been taught
to see ourselves.
We haven't been taught by the world to eat curses and spit blessings back out to the
people who threw the manas.
We've been taught to lament how unjust it is that we were cursed.
We've been taught that the problem is the world is that I'm a righteous person who's suffering.
I'm not a righteous person.
And that's not why I'm suffering.
But we've been taught to look at ourselves that way.
The problem is the bad things happening to me, not the way I'm living my life and the
choices I'm making and how to receive the things of life.
We've been taught essentially to CR.
and to act and behave as victims continuously.
And a victim being a victim perpetually
is the opposite of being invincible.
It's the opposite of being unable to be harmed.
And so to me, this is the really important practice
that we can derive from these things
that we've been talking about.
There's too much of our lives that's consumed by fear, fear of being hurt, fear of struggle,
fear of criticism, fear of the opinions of other people.
There's too much of our life that spent nursing old wounds.
There's too much of our life that's spent wanting people to treat us the way our...
Other people, or life itself, or even dare I say, God, to treat us the way we think we deserve to be treated.
And nowhere near enough time spent, turning the way life does treat us to good.
And getting ourselves into a position where, in and with Christ, we are victorious over all of the troubles that come to us in this life.
Amen. Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much everyone for listening.
We didn't take calls this time because this is a pre-recorded show, pre-recorded show.
But we would still love to hear from you. You can email us at LordOfSpirits.atationfeat.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can also leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash LordOfSpirits.
And join us for our live broadcast. The next one should Lord of Women Be Live.
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month that's
the 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
The horsemen are drawing nearer
on the leather steeds they ride.
They've come to take your life.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page
and you can join our discussion group.
We've reviews and ratings and all the appropriate places.
And share this show with somebody
that has been to benefit from.
And finally, be sure to go to
www.engshafethe.com.scope support
and help make sure we and lots of other
AFR podcasters stay on the air.
On through the dead of night with the four horsemen ride,
choose your face.
and died.
Thank you, good night.
And on that cheery note from Father Stephen,
may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
And the number of them was 10,000 times
Ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory
and blessing.
Revelation chapter five verses 11 through 12.
This is Frederica, Matthew's Green.
and you're listening to ancient faith radio, timeless Christianity 24 hours a day.
I'm Robin Phillips, the Nostek buster at ancient faith.
Did you know that God's kingdom is of this earth?
that the resurrection totally changed history?
Did you know that because of Christ's substitutionary tonement, we can build for God's kingdom?
Did you know that as we participate in God's kingdom building work, we make the world a better place?
If any of these questions surprise you, it could be because you have been unconsciously
with some form of implicit narcissism.
But that's okay.
I used to be a Nostec, and in my latest book,
rediscovering the goodness of creation,
I have shared my journey from Nosticism
to Orthodox Christianity.
It's a journey I invite you all to travel with me.
Rediscovering the goodness of creation
is available at store.anchonfaith.com.
O my Savior, reign in the desert, homilies from Holy Trinity Greek Orthodox Cathedral.
Father Rapostal Lose Hill, Dean of Holy Trinity Greek Orthodox Cathedral of Phoenix, Arizona,
delivers a timely message and a humorous and straightforward preaching style as he draws
from his various life adventures to underscore the power of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
Christ to save and to heal broken humanity.
He was Father Apostle Most.
The length is now half over.
You can believe it.
We find ourselves celebrating the elevation of the life-giving cross of Jesus Christ.
One of three feasts that we keep throughout the course of the year.
The elevation, the exaltation, the procession of the cross, the third Sunday of the length,
the 14th of September and the 1st of August.
And the way that we
view the cross is essential for us. It is the way that we ultimately view salvation and
God and everything that has to do with our worth of our Christian faith. So it's not surprising
that we see in the West today a great deal of reluctance to talk about the cross. And as I want
to set forth today by using the words of others primarily, the difference between the Eastern
you the or the
the Orthodox view of the cross and the Western view,
let's say the Catholic and the Protestant view of the cross.
And we love it.
They are truly diametrically opposite views.
And it is essential that we come to understand that.
It's not a small thing to be an Orthodox Christian
and it's not an easy thing to be an Orthodox Christian
in the Western world today.
So let's begin.
Dr. Havine Acrocentina wrote a beautiful book
that I am reading now called
thinking orthodox, I commend it to you
is something that you ought to read available in ancient faith.
And she describes in there the difference between
the orthodox Thronema, which we'd say would be worldview,
way of life, our outlook, our ethos,
our zeitgeist, a supplyable word,
and a Western Thronema.
And they are substantially different,
particularly where it comes to our view of salvation.
So we begin then with Dr. Constantino's
Okay.
instruction of the teaching of on-som of Canterbury, who in 1094 wrote a book, a paper that would
become the basis for how the Catholic and the Protestant world with, and I'd be so bold
as to say, Miss Perci, the Cross, as opposed to the way that Orthodox Christians from the
Holy Fathers and from the tradition given to the Church views the Cross.
Let's begin.
He writes
Some of Connobernate wrote why God became man in 1094,
which began with a presumption that God is just,
and sin is an offense against God that demands punishment.
Humans commit the sins, so a human must pay the penalty.
However, no human is able to pay such a huge penalty.
Only God could possibly pay such a high price, therefore,
God had to become man.
God was incarnate in the person of Jesus.
Christ in order to die on the cross and satisfy divine justice. That is not the Orthodox
view. To continue this view commonly known as substitutionary atonement or another way
as penal substitutionary atonement has deep roots and is accepted in some form by most
Western Christians. The broad acceptance of Ansams logic speaks to the extreme legalism
and the radical departure from the
apostolic tradition that had developed in the medieval West. It is ironic that
Anson's conclusion was so readily accepted in the West. The Catholic Church
affirms the development of doctrine which we do not. The teaching of the Catholic
Church that doctrine develops hence medieval scholars are more insightful than
patristic fathers and modern scholars are more insightful than medieval
scholars that is the opposite of what we believe is worth it.
And the Catholic Church holds that the medieval and scholastic theologians understood the faith and expressed its concepts in a manner
again superior to the fathers. And yet as she says here, and Psalms theology is crude, faulty, shallow, simplistic, and manifestly inferior to the
understanding of salvation among the church fathers. And then she quotes Metropolitan pedophiles of Locals, a beautiful,
one that we should be familiar with. She says a heat
accurately assesses the fundamental theological flaw in Anson's theory. When he
points out that this view in fact makes God subject to the laws of necessity. God
then requires the satisfaction and propitiation, thus the purpose of the
incarnation of the world in Anson's view and that of the Western world and his
sacrifice on the cross was the propagiotic
of divine justice which was offended by man's sin.
He continues to remark that not only is this
invalid from an Orthodox perspective,
but it can even be considered heretical.
A point of view that would certainly surprise Western
Christians because its theory is so widely accepted.
So we begin to see then the challenge between us,
between a correct Orthodox view of the cross
and a Western view of the cross.
This view of sin is rejected by orthodox Christianity because among other things it suggests
that God is the problem and not humanity.
God by nature is free of any necessity and of any self-interest, of any egoic concern.
Without question, the death of Christ and the cross was a sacrifice and redemption for
the human race, but that is the only one model by which we're going to...
understand the entire land of salvation, the death of cries in the cross was not transactional.
And substitutionary atonement, I'll say it, heresy is 100 percent transactional.
So then there can be no surprise that we see within Christendom today, perhaps small
sea, that there's always this idea of a transaction taking place.
Again, this is not the Orthodox view.
that the cross is not transactional nor demanded by the Father nor necessary to satisfy divine
justice. Furthermore, such language is unworthy of God and even blasphemous because it lowers God
to the level of sinful humanity. Part of us likes the idea of a vengeful God because then our
enemies get smitten, right? We love to be God for a day, throwing lightning bolts at the people who
offended us in some way. Again, this is not the word
the rocks point view.
Quoting Metropolitan Blockus again,
it is sinful to describe to God the characteristic features
of fallen men by alleging, for example,
that God is angry and vengeful.
God is not angry and or vengeful.
And therefore, that he must be propitiated and appeased.
Such an attitude wants to make it appear
that it is God who needs securing and not men,
but this is sacrilegious.
sinful man who is characterized by egoism and arrogance is offended.
We cannot say that God is offended.
Consequently, sin is not an insult to God who must be cured, but our own illness, and
therefore we need to be cured.
And we'll talk about that in a minute.
St. Gregory the Great, in his second, Possible Orations speaks of this, and he says words
here that are very famous that are quoted frequently.
Speaking about how we as Orthodox, how the Apostolic fathers viewed the cross, and the sacrifice
that Jesus Christ made to slaughter death on our behalf.
And this is what he says.
Now we are to examine another fact in dogma neglected by most people, but in my judgment
well worth inquiring into.
And then he asked the question, to whom was that blood offered that was shed for us and
why was it shed?
I mean the precious and famous
blood of our God and high priests and sacrifice. We were detained in bondage to the evil one,
sold under sin, and receiving pleasure and exchange for wickedness. Now since a ransom
belongs only to him who holds in bondage, I ask to whom was this offered and for what cause.
And then his famous words, he says, if the ransom was paid to the evil one, then he says,
by upon the outreach.
They'll have none of it.
If the robber receives ransom, not only from God,
but a ransom that consists of God himself,
and the person of Jesus Christ hanging on the cross,
and has such an illustrious payment for his tyranny,
a payment for who's sake it would have been right for him
to have left us alone altogether.
So we see again this broad and un...
bridgeable distance between the orthodox view of the cross and the western view of the cross.
And we hear that in the hymnaology of the church, you say,
then, while what do we actually believe?
If we don't believe that, they got his angry,
and vengeful, luster punish, and smite that we sinned,
he was offended, his justice demanded an answer,
he could kill us, but who cares, we're going to die anyway.
So he sins his son Jesus to kill him to get it out of his system.
Does that sound?
like a God you want to serve? Because not a God that I would serve. Nor should you. So what do we
believe? In the resurrection of Opuletikian today of Ecos VIII, the seventh thorn, we say,
by means of your cross, O Lord, you abolished death. To the robber, hanging to his right,
you opened the paragots. The temptation of the mere bragging women, the lamentation you
transform them to joy.
At the Kathisma for the cross that we are saying today in Mattins, we hear this.
Of all the tree in the garden, that's the tree in the knowledge of good and evil, the fruit
of which Adam and Eve ate and found themselves kicked out of the garden of Eden.
Of all the tree in the garden, stripped of snake and by its taste did the enemy bring
in death.
Now the tree of the cross, which for all mankind is varying the garment of life, was planted
upon the earth.
And therefore, as all the world filled with joy,
as we see it revered today, let us O peoples cry aloud
together into God in faith, full of glory is your house, O Lord.
So we see a juxtaposition between the tree in the garden of Eden
that produced a fruit that led to death
and the tree of the cross planted on Gha'gatha
that produced the fruit that brings us life.
So we see then the narrative is one of, of, of,
of a disease, of a lamentable 100% lethal toxin and virus called sin, which if we leave untreated in our lives will kill our soul and consign us to the flames of hell.
Yes, but it is 100% curable.
So let's just do that.
That's simple.
We'll talk about that in a minute.
Continuing our hymnology, the echoes of the
cross today. The nether were below was trembling today,
Hades and death before one of Atrinity. The earth was convulsing and the
worms of hell seeing you coward and theory at creation all rejoicing with the
prophets, Sings and Ode to triumph to you, our Redeemer and our God who now has
destroyed the power of death to Adam and to those who were born after him,
let a shalt and triumph and cry aloud, a tree has brought this man back in,
Come out.
faithful to the resurrection. So we see again and again in our
himnology that the cross is that which vanquishes death. Every
time we celebrate a feast of the cross, we give you a flower. We
don't give you a nail. We don't give you a writ of commutation of
your sentence. This is not a penal institution. That was the
early heresy corrected the church said
know this is a hospital. It's a hospital which is cured. And the means by which our
cure is affected is the cross and the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ. How then do we embrace
the cross? This all sounds very theological. I have no doubt. There's more I'd love to
read for you. I don't have the time. How though do we embrace the cross? Because it's not
enough for us to say that Christ has destroyed death so I can go about my very, my Mary,
business to never give it another thought. The cross is a weapon. It's a weapon that we use
to slaughter not only death in the sense of an existential category when we stop breathing,
but the death that resides in each of us. Again, Ezekiel the Prophet says, the soul that sins will
die. Say Paul says, the wages of sin is death. How can we then kill death within us but by the cross?
by using a
as it is intended as a weapon in our arsenal to help us defeat the death that resides within
each of us through sin.
How do we appropriate the cross?
Beloved, we don't need to overthink this when the middle of Great Lent, where in the
middle Sunday of Great Lent, when it's become hard, when we don't like it, when we've
gone through our Lent and recipes already.
but you'd even come to a few of the service.
maybe we're trying to do our prayer rule at home reading the daily scriptures and we don't like the fact that we feel
constrained somehow or obligated somehow by this expectation of this ought to be a special time for us but it is
in great length and in the oscacies of the church that our flesh is subdued by the power of the cross
by not being self-directed
by bending and shaping our will to the will of God in simple
ways by keeping the fast. I said yesterday in the Bible study, Christians that don't
or that us Christians that don't keep the fast will find themselves with very little to
offer when temptation comes because their flesh is untamed and they are self-directed.
And they'll say to themselves, I don't need to follow the fast to be a good person and
that's 100% correct if being a good person had anything at all to do with being a Christian.
love and
And we appropriate the power of the cross as that would slaughter death on our behalf
by the simple, seemingly insignificant things that we do in our lives that show the
Lordship of Jesus Christ.
We cannot call Him Kideos if He's not really the boss.
We can't valibly say Kideolayson.
If there are parts of our life that we're withholding from His Lordship, the cross is
by which God destroyed death.
And it is essential for us to understand what the cross does and does not mean.
Because once we see it through eastern eyes, then we will have no further hesitation
to run to confession.
Because unlike the Western Church, you don't come to confession to be judged,
to be condemned, to be told that you're unworthy.
Of course you're unworthy.
We're human being.
were never made worthy on our own merits.
The Western Church speaks of merits, we do not.
Our worth and its resides in the one to whom we are united
through the incarnation by the sacraments of the Church
and by the daily living out of our lives
as Orthodox Christians.
So we love it today, we celebrate the Holy Cross
of Jesus Christ, but we do so in an Orthodox way.
which again does
And it showed us an angry, vengeful God who had to kill his son to get it out of the
system.
But God of love.
And the one who voluntarily ascended the cross.
It was at nails that held Jesus to the wit of the cross.
It was His love and His desire to save us and to redeem us.
So the love of His, celebrate the cross of the day, let us do something with joy in our
hearts.
This great treasury given to us.
in the Church.
Rain in the Desert.
Father of Postal Loose Hill is Dean of Holy Trinity Greek Orthodox Cathedral in Phoenix,
Arizona.
This has been a list of supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
On the web at ancientfaith.com.
Healing the unresolved, putting the past in the past.
Father Joshua McCool guides those who have suffered painful experiences and continue to live in shame and isolation as result of these hardships.
Father Joshua is the author of Healing Your Wounded Soul, growing from pain to peace and also healing work, giving humanity a second chance, both published by Ancient Faith Publishing, and is also a licensed counselor in the state of Pennsylvania.
Here he is with today's program.
Hello listeners and welcome back to another episode of Healing the Unresolved, Putting the Past in the Past.
Today's episode, we're going to be responding to a very interesting question and one that's very different than one we might expect or anticipate.
And the question of we're going to be answering in this episode is, are there any movies that are recommended that might be helpful?
in the healing work or in the healing process.
And I would begin by answering that question.
Certainly, yes, there are.
But for each person, the movie is going to be different.
And really what we want to look for are
what are movies that resonate, or even a movie that has a certain part
or parts that may be resonate with us.
And most of us have experienced this when watching
a movie. To resonate means if something resonates with us, it means that it affects or it appeals
to us in a very personal or emotional way even. That even on a deep unconscious level, we very
much connect or relate with the scene that we are witnessing, and it can often provoke a very
powerful emotional response in us. And most of us have had those moments of resonance
or something resonates with us very...
deeply and often those are good moments. And so we're looking for movies that resonate with us
or maybe that even have certain themes. And certainly there's some, you know, certainly feel
good movies out there that, you know, are kind of warm and fuzzy and make everybody feel good. But
that's not what we're talking about tonight. We're talking about movies that maybe have a much more
powerful or deeper theme to them that are connected and
related to the more common life experiences that we have and that most of us could relate to.
And so what happens is, so when there's a movie out there, or even one scene from a movie
that just resonates with us, you know, it's one of those moments where we're sitting watching this movie perfectly fine.
And then all of a sudden, it just gets right through to our heart and could reduce somebody even to,
to just this Terry mess.
And I think most of us
could can certainly relate to that.
And so when that happens, if and when we have had that experience where some part of
the movie just grabs us, what's happening is that the imagery or the scene or the life
experience we're watching play out in this movie, it is bypassing our conscious mind and
And it's going, it's tapping right into our unconscious mind and it's bringing out a motion.
directly from the unconscious mind. And so in essence, when we have this experience,
it is bypassing our defenses. So many of us have defenses that we're employing on an unconscious level to hold certain
negative emotion at bay. But those defenses are usually guarding us and what experiences we have and may be
be protecting us from feeling certain emotions that might be uncomfortable or you-
overwhelming. However, we might notice that if we watch somebody else have an experience,
or we hear someone else share a story, or we witness a scene in a movie that just gets us,
that just resonates. The defenses are not activated because it's not about us, because we are not the
source of that or experience. We are seeing it in someone else. The source is not ourselves.
And so it just blows right towards...
defenses and it brings up that emotion that's been all backed up and it gets it up and out.
And so from that perspective, it's a very positive thing. And so in fact, this question is
really an excellent question. So certain movies can actually be very helpful in the healing process.
Okay, because when we have this experience, it feels good, like liberating moment.
And so once we have that moment and we're like, wow, what just happened?
What was it about that scene that resonated?
What did it remind me of?
Once we identify this, it could become a very useful tool.
And so very often what's happening is that movie or that scene is capturing our life story
or some aspect of our life story, such as the story of a specific life experience.
So
So we can use these moments or discoveries to kind of leapfrog ahead in our own healing
work.
And that's because these moments of resonance can help us capture a certain theme to our
life or experience, perhaps that we had not yet been able to articulate up until that
point.
You know, we sometimes we just have general themes or a hunch or a vague inkling that
It's something to do with this.
But sometimes if we follow and track those moments of resonance, something resonates with
us, especially in a movie, it can often lead us to our core experience and enable us to
actually articulate it in a very succinct and concise way in which helps it feel more
manageable and more easily to address.
Because it's not like this vague, free floating experience that we know is out there, but
can't quite articulate
So these moments too, they help us to find ourselves.
Sometimes when people are holding back a lot of emotion under the surface, they can start to feel emotionally numb.
And our emotions get repressed and they get suppressed.
And we just numb out because we might not be very good at selecting out certain emotions.
certain emotions. So basically in order to suppress certain negative emotions, we tend to just suppress all emotions.
emotion. Sometimes even the positive emotion, because for some of us, it's hard to feel
positive feelings without letting the negative feelings out. It's very hard to hold down one
part of our emotional world, but letting another part out. It's usually too much to control.
So very often people will experience emotional numbness when they are suppressing or holding
back a negative emotion. Maybe they're just not ready to deal with it. Maybe it's overwhelming.
we have a hard time tolerating negative.
or maybe we're just tired and not ready to deal with it.
But these moments can help us find our starting point
to resume the healing work if indeed we had gotten distracted
from our healing work.
Sometimes it's just one single part of a movie like that,
or one movie could just totally refresh us,
a remind us of our core experience,
and kind of re-reveal to us.
are starting point. It brings focus, a sense of where our emotions are coming from. That's how
powerful and telling and revealing these moments of resonance can be. And so what are some movie
examples, even, that maybe have very powerful themes to them that are not just pure thrills
in entertainment. And certainly that even really don't have any violence in them. So there's a number
of them.
And again, there's so many more out there,
but I just chose a few to use a special example.
Certainly this list is not exhaustive in any way.
So I wanted to start with an old movie.
This must have been back from like 1990 or something.
That movie, A Field of Dreams.
And many of us when we reflect on that movie
is all that baseball movie with Kevin Costner,
in which this farmer, you know.
Just creates the space ball field in his the middle of his cornfield and all the sudden these old-time baseball players appear and start playing baseball again
Of course for anybody's familiar with the movie or that watches the movie you'll see there's a much deeper
meaning
In that movie that might resonate with many of us
So that whole movie field of dreams is about unresolved grief
It's about second chances in closure
And so to kind of relay this universal experience that we all have, you know, issues of loss and unresolved grief and sometimes the second chances and closure is it presents Kevin Costner is the main character, you know, this father who's at midlife.
uh... he's kind of having some financial problems he and he's starting to feel
like his father before his father passed away
and uh... as the movie goes on
It's not until the genius of this movie is that it's not revealed into the very end, the
very emotional ending.
What brought about this miraculous field of dreams were all these people show up who had
lack of closure in their life to get second chances, whether it was to play professional
baseball again or whatever it was.
And so at the very end of the movie, it's revealed that it was his yearning for his father.
His father died before they could wreak.
in exile, and they couldn't connect.
And his father tried to use baseball to connect with him.
And you know, just wanted to talk baseball with him,
wanted him to play baseball.
He wanted nothing to do with it.
And it actually led to a fracture in their relationship.
And so it makes sense that this, so of course it's fiction,
but nevertheless it conveys a point.
So his unresolved grief this yearning
led to him to create this baseball field, which
was actually an act.
It was an act of unresolved grief, trying to connect with the departed, trying to connect with somebody we didn't get closure with.
Many of us have done that. You know, in very unique ways we try to replace lost objects or people or we seek a connection with them.
And so here he, that's why it was a baseball field. And then at the end it's revealed that it was his yearning for his father that created this miracle, this phenomenon.
at the very end of the movie.
you know, all the baseball players are packing up their stuff and leaving the field and disappearing
back into this cornfield. And there's one player lingering behind. And he's getting ready to
go into his house and he looks and all this said and he realizes it's his father. And it's
a very dramatic emotional part of the movie. And it's when his father was younger before
he had his father had had all these negative setbacks in his life. He looked fresh and young.
And he went up and talked to him.
they kind of recognized each other and then they got to have one game of catch, which he would never
give his father growing up. And so here this beautiful field of dreams, which was created by his
unresolved grief, gave him the second chance to have a game of catch with his father that his
father, that's really what his father wanted. And he got closure. It's such a beautiful theme to it.
And, you know, a lot of people don't realize just how deep that movie is in the themes.
it. And so that scene in the movie is one that often kind of jumps up and bites people and really
gets through their defenses and brings up unresolved grief. And when we have been holding back
emotion for a long time and something gets through our defenses right to our heart,
we feel alive again because it's healthy and normal to express emotion. Of course, as long as it's
not hurting anyone.
else but we're not meant to live like zombies just emotionally, not feeling anything like
that. That's usually a sign that we are repressing and holding back a painful emotions.
And so another movie that I'd like to take a moment and focus on is also an older movie
and this movie was called Cast Away with Tom Hanks. And it was that movie about that FedEx.
He was a FedEx executive who...
was getting ready to propose to his girlfriend and then he gets on this plane, the FedEx plane
that's flying over nowhere in the middle of the Pacific and the thunderstorm, the plane,
I think gets hit by lightning and crashes has to ditch in the middle of the Pacific Ocean and
he's the only one that survives. He gets on this raft and wakes up in this tiny island in the middle
of nowhere in the Pacific Island. And there are many parallels between his experience, the movie,
and
healing work or the healing process.
Okay?
And so if you haven't watched this movie, watch it because each of us has our own
island, you know, sometimes when we've had traumatic or painful experiences or
losses in our life, you know, it's a unique experience that maybe only we had or
that we only experienced as we did.
We may have, there may have been other people in our family that experienced it too,
but our personal response to that experience is unique.
and the healing work that we have
to do is unique. And so for each one of us that experience becomes like this kind of isolated
island that we live on. Right? And so each of us has our own island that we have to work
our way out of. And so, and so in the beginning of the healing work, we have no clue what to do.
Kind of like him in the movie. And the movie does this masterful job. You can just feel it.
Here he is, the city guy who has no idea how to survive in the wild. And here he is just
sitting on this beat.
trying to figure out how he's going to survive. But then suddenly as the movie goes on, he
begins to gain experience and he becomes like the season veteran. He kind of looks like
this wild person who's just become this master of living outdoors. And that's what happens
to us in the healing work. You know, once we confront our island, our experience that
we're on, and we start to become resilient, and we start to become very seasoned and experienced
with the abs and flows of the healing work.
and healing from trauma and painful experiences.
And eventually we might be ready to move on from that island.
And that's exactly what happens.
He reaches that point where he's finally ready and has all the tools he needs to finally
set off to see and to the unknown and leave the island behind.
Of course everybody who knows this movie knows about Wilson.
What is Wilson?
and
is this volleyball that washed up on shore on this island.
And he picked it up and he kept it with him.
And one day he got a cut on his hand,
so there was blood on his hand,
and he must have grabbed hold of the ball
and it left this red hand mark on the ball,
but it looked like a face.
And so he kind of decorated it more
and gave it some features,
and he started talking to it,
because he had been alone on this island for so long.
And so the ball became he named it will
because it was from the that's the volleyball company Wilson and he would talk to this ball,
but he was actually projecting part of himself onto this ball. So rather than talk to himself and
go mad for how many years he was on this island, he treated the ball and the face on the ball like
it was another person Wilson who he would talk to. So he would use this ball to actually talk to
himself. You see? And he had to do that to survive. Or else...
he could have gone mad. And so it served a purpose for a time. This was his buddy. He talked
to this ball day and night, and it helped him survive psychologically. And so the time came
where it was ready for him to escape from this island, this place of isolation. And there's
a very powerful part of the movie where he finally, you know, he he had tried to escape
on this raft before, but there was a series of waves on this island that he could not get
passed. Finally, he later in his
cast away experience, he found a way to fix this sale to this raft. So when the wind caught it,
it pushed him over this giant wave that had almost destroyed him when he tried to escape the first
time. And he made it. And he broke free from his isolation and being trapped on that island.
And it's one of the most beautiful parts of the movie. At one point, the camera shows him looking
back, kind of wistfully and apprehensively.
as his island fades into the clouds, into the rain clouds out of view. And he starts to look forward
into the unknown. You see, and so his island fades from view and he kind of looks back at it,
almost nistogically, wistfully, apprehensively, and he sails into the unknown to try to rejoin humanity.
Much like many do who are going through the healing work and trying to heal from their own
painful and and and tremendous.
and so there's many more parallels with this movie.
And so at this part of the movie, there's this whale following him.
And this whale kind of just gently follows him and watches him
and shows himself once in a while.
He observes Tom Hanks.
And then when necessary, he sprays him with water to wake him up
at very providential times.
And so, and then not long comes the real tear-jerker part of this movie.
jerk or part of this
movie, which it can really resonate with a lot of people, certainly anyone that has suffered
loss in their life.
And even if you haven't, it's a tough part from many people.
So there's a part where he's sleeping on the raft and all of a sudden the ball, Wilson,
who he has projected, who helped him survive while he was on the island, that he had projected
part of himself onto because he had no one else to talk to.
Suddenly the ball falls off the raft and into the water.
the wheel.
sprays him with some water like to wake him up and he sits up but the ball the current has taken it
and he panics and he starts trying to paddle towards it and then he jumps in the water and he starts
to find himself between his life raft which is the key to take him back to humanity and civilization
and Wilson that's drifting away and he doesn't know which one to do and he's frantically crying for
for Wilson. He grabs the rope that's attached to his raft and he...
He tries to pull it along to go after Wilson and all of a sudden he can't and he starts to
drown.
And he had to let go.
He had to give up something that he had been using to cope with his painful, this isolating
experience.
And it's why I think it's probably one of the most emotional part of any movie.
And he had to let Wilson go.
I finally chose to go back to his raft, which was his only home.
hope to get him back to civilization and rejoin humanity and then it shows him a drift on
the siege, a sobbing and weeping, because he had to let go.
He had to let go of something that soon he was not going to need anymore because he was
rejoining humanity.
And it's very hard, I think, for many people to watch that and not get a terriide, but for
those of us who have suffered loss in our life, even a life-stage transition.
We're not even just talking about trauma here, painful life experiences, but even just a stage in our life where we have to let go of something.
And many times as we're adjusting to a loss, we have a hard time letting go. We try to hold on to things.
We're doing things in our life maybe that are not healthy because we're not moving to the acceptance stage.
And we reach this point where we suddenly realize we have to let go.
Maybe it was a stage of life, maybe it was someone who passed...
the way because if we don't we're gonna drown. We're gonna drown and we won't survive and we have to
let something go and we accept the present and start to move towards the future. And that movie just
captures that. And that's a part of a movie that often resonates in a very profound way. And so if we,
you can even point YouTube that clip, but I would encourage you the cast away Wilson part, but I would
I encourage you
to watch the movie because it's just it's a moment of profound grief and so anyways. And so the whale
in many ways almost kind of represents God in our life through the healing work. So if you watch
that movie and you see how the whale kind of cautiously follows him keeps an eye on him and almost
intervenes when he needs to. For example, when the rescue, when the huge boat's going by, it would
but had missed him so the wheel sprays him with
water and it wakes him up so he sits up and the people on the boat see him and he gets rescued.
And I just realized I totally just spoiled the movie. So yeah well okay. I can't take that one back.
So my apologies for that. Nevertheless, I have to believe most of you who are hearing this have
probably watched the movie. So anyways, back to the original point. The whale is like God in
in order.
life. As we go through the healing work and the healing process, God follows us. He keeps
an eye on us. He lets us do the work and figure things out. But he stays with us, keeps an
eye on us. And when he needs to, he intervenes when we need it the most. You see, so there's
just so many beautiful parallels that movie cast away between the movie story and our
own healing work and healing experience. And remember that so that isolated island is
like our island of emotional
experience that we often find ourselves on due to painful or traumatic experiences.
And so another program we might watch, and this one, as I'm a little different now, this
one is actually not fiction, but nonfiction.
It's a historical, it's a World War II series called The Pacific.
And it's really for anybody to watch.
It's very powerful.
a very well-made, kind of like that series, Band of Brothers, but this one was for the Pacific
Theater in World War II. And it focuses around, there's a number of main characters, but there's
especially one main character, and this young man named Eugene, and he kind of becomes the
prevalent character as the series goes on. And he was just, you know, a boy when he goes off,
Like so many young men were enrolled were two but they came back men.
And it was hard to adjust to normal life.
You know, they left from high school as boys,
and suddenly after four years of war and horrific experiences,
they come back to their bedrooms,
that they have left from high school,
and their sports penins are up in their books,
and they just can't relate or connect.
And sometimes, their painful or traumatic experiences
in our life can do that to us.
And so, in episode 10,
so if you don't want to watch the whole series,
But they don't blame you.
don't. If you have an interest in history, I would encourage you to do so because it makes
the ending all the more powerful and resonates even more. But if we don't want to, maybe
go to the end of episode 10, the final episode of the Pacific. And there's actually, you
can YouTube this video clip. I think if you put the Pacific ending Eugene. And so this
character Eugene, you know, he's just this battle hard and veteran.
He turns into a...
a man during the war and you know you're used to seeing him with his helmet and his rifle
and his uniform and suddenly he comes home and to his home state of it might have been
why do I think maybe it was Alabama I'm not sure which state it was but nevertheless
it's a true story and he wrote a book and about his experience so his father was a physician
And his father knew he was suffering from post-traumatic stress, basically.
his father had treated shell shock survivors from World War One.
And so his father took him out one day to try to connect with his son.
This is how this series ended.
This epic ten-part series ends with this moment.
And he takes some hunting to go hunt pigeons or doves or whatever down near this creek.
So they drive up in the pickup truck and he looks like a boy.
He doesn't look like a man anymore. He's wearing civilian...
clothing and he's with his dad and he's kind of moping behind behind his dad a little bit.
And so he's walking, his dad's walking ahead.
And for the first time since the war, he finds himself carrying a firearm, walking through
the wilderness.
And that was it.
Up until that point, he could not show any emotion.
He was stuffed up.
All his emotion was repressed and suppressed from the war.
He had all these powerful losses.
horrific experiences and they were bottled up tight and all it took and
This is true story this happened in his life all it took was this one experience and it all came out
And it's one of the most beautiful movie parts
I think I've ever seen and so he's walking and all the sudden
It's a trigger and
It just he collapses and he starts sobbing and so he's a little boy again and here this this battle heart and
that you watch through this series suddenly just crumbles and his dad holds him and embraces him because he knows what's going on
And he says to his dad. I'm sorry dad. I can't I can't I can't do this because it reminded him too much of his war experience
and it was just such a beautiful tender moment
and so for people who are watching that to get to the point if they have had
traumatic experiences in their life where they just have a hard time, you know,
people understanding or connecting with others or feeling isolated or that I don't think I need to say
anymore if you watch that part you'll know what I'm talking about. It's one of those parts that just
grabs hold of our heart and if it resonates with us go with that a little bit. Ask us what's the
parallel? What's the theme? What does that remind us of? And so sometimes watching movies that show
other people's losses.
in their grieving process helps us.
You see?
And so this is just a few suggestions.
Finally, there's some other movies I won't go into detail.
Another one I recommend is the movie Awakening's.
And that one maybe is not so resonating as the others.
But it's a powerful movie because in the healing work,
we are like those people.
And the movie Awakening's is a true story
about Robin Williams at Place of R-
He's either a neurologist or psychiatrist.
I think he's a neurologist at a hospital in the Bronx.
It's a true story.
And back in the 20s or 30s, there was this encephalitis that went around.
It was contagious.
And people went into these catatonic states for years, decades.
And he had tried playing around with this medication that in the summer of 1960, something,
all the people in this ward that took this medicine had an awakening where they were alive again,
interacting, but then after a few months.
or the effects of the medicine wore off, but for those few months they were alive again.
It's a very powerful movie that resonates with us because it reminds us
to use the time that we have to stay awake and do the healing work.
And I won't say anymore about that because that's another one I would suggest.
And many of us who are listening to this could, I'm sure, add to movies that they know of.
that resonate and that sometimes when they watch it, it helps refresh them for the healing
work, the healing process.
It helps bring them back to where they need to be so they can resume doing all the work
that they are doing.
So yes, to answer the question, movies can be helpful in our healing work.
And sometimes if we're feeling emotionally stuck, if we're feeling emotionally numb and
We need something to get those emotions flowing again.
put that movie on or watch that certain part of a movie because remember we're tricking
our defenses.
Sometimes our psychological defenses want to protect us from negative emotion.
So we can't we try to feel the emotion and we can't.
But if we see it in someone else or we watch it on the screen, the defenses are not activated
because the source of it is not us.
It's something else or someone else.
And that and it cuts right past the defenses and brings up that emotion.
so we can get it up and...
out and feel alive again and not flat or emotionally numb.
And so that's just one of the ways the movies can work and help us.
So I really, that was really all the questions that have submitted, of course, have been excellent.
So I hope you enjoyed today's podcast episode.
And again, if you haven't read the two books that are out there, please do.
I'm really seeking feedback on the second.
book. So if you've read it, please consider doing a review on, you know, each and
faith website or any of the others where it's being sold. So it's just just hoping
to hear that it's helped people out there. I know hasn't been out too long, but if
you have a moment to do that, I'd be grateful. All right. Have a blessed day and
we'll be back soon for the next episode.
Healing the unresolved.
Putting the past.